- Stanford University.
- Okay, welcome to lecture eight,
Stanford CS193p, spring of 2020.
I'm gonna try to keep
the slides short today
so we can jump into another big demo,
but I need to talk about conceptual stuff
behind a couple of things
we're gonna do in the demo,
namely UserDefaults, which
is a very lightweight,
persistent store that we're just gonna use
for demo purposes.
And then, the main meaty topic
of today, which is gestures,
getting input from your user
using their fingers basically.
So, let's talk about
this UserDefaults thing.
Before I do that, I wanna talk
about persistence in general.
By persistence I just mean that
making things stick on your iOS device
even when you quit your
app and restart it.
And there's numerous ways
to make data persist.
You can put it in a file system, iOS.
Basically there's a Unix
machine underneath it all,
and it has a Unix file system,
and you can certainly store
things in the file system.
I hope to cover that later in the quarter.
You could put things in a SQL database
or some other database.
iOS has an awesome
framework called CoreData
that essentially does an object
oriented programming layer
on top of a SQL database.
Really fantastic.
Don't think we're gonna
get to that this quarter,
but I'd like to at least talk
about it later in the quarter.
Of course, we can store things in iCloud.
That's great way,
because it's shared
between all of our devices.
And, in fact, there's an entire
framework called CloudKit,
which let's us do database
operations essentially,
that get stored in the cloud.
So that's a cool way.
And there's many third
party options as well.
Different frameworks
provided by third parties
that do the kind of same
thing, network databases,
places to store things, et cetera.
But one of the simplest
ways to store things
is using something called UserDefaults,
and you can think of it as
a persistent Dictionary.
It feels a lot like a Dictionary
that just sticks on disk,
but it really should only be used,
when you're shipping your app,
you probably only wanna use UserDefaults
for user preferences, small little things.
You don't wanna use it to, for example,
store your documents,
which is what we're gonna do in our demo,
it's why I'm telling
you about UserDefaults,
so we need some lightweight
way to store our documents,
so we're gonna do it.
But I mean, UserDefaults
is valuable though,
for storing these lightweight things,
but you're gonna see there's
some quirkiness to it as well.
Now UserDefaults is quite limited
in the type of data it can store.
This is not just a full
database or a full Dictionary,
you can put any type you want in there.
It's an ancient API I call it,
it's been around a long time,
it far predates SwiftUI or even Swift,
and its API is a little strange
for those of you in this class
who are now really used
to functional programming.
But if we squint at this API,
we can make it look close enough to Swift
and functional programming
for it to fit in.
The data that's stored in UserDefaults
is called a property list.
Now, of property list is
not a protocol or a struct,
or any tangible thing from Swift,
'cause this is all pretty Swift.
But property list is
really just a concept.
It's an idea.
And that idea is that it's
any combination of Strings,
Ints, Bools, floating point
numbers like Float or Double,
Dates, Datas, which are bags
of bits, just arbitrary data,
Arrays and Dictionaries.
So you put any combination
of those together,
like an Array that it has
Dictionaries with Strings
as the keys and Ints as the values,
that would be a property list.
A kinda goofy one, but that
would be a property list
'cause all the things in
there are one of these things.
So that's all we can store there,
we can't store anything else.
If you wanna store anything else,
you have to convert it into
a property list somehow.
Now, a really powerful way in Swift
to convert an arbitrary
struct into a property list
is using this Codable protocol,
and I'm just going to put
that off and show you that
in the demo, rather than having
a bunch of slides about it.
And you'll see, pretty
quickly, how Codable works.
It's a great way to turn
a struct into a Data,
and of course a Data, a bag
of bits, is a property list,
and so we can throw it in UserDefaults.
And we'll see that all in the demo.
Now, why is the API of UserDefaults weird?
Well, because prominently in
that API, is a type in Swift,
which we have not talked about,
intentionally, called Any.
So Any is basically a
type that means untyped.
If something's of type Any,
it's like it doesn't really have a type.
Well Swift is a strongly typed language,
it does not like Any.
Any is antithetical to Swift.
But, it has this type Any just
for backwards compatibility
with things like UserDefaults.
So, we really don't wanna
have anything to do with Any
as SwiftUI and Swift
programmers in general.
But we wanna use UserDefaults,
so we're gonna try to ignore
Any in UserDefaults' API,
which is a challenge, but you can do it.
And yet we still wanna understand
how to use UserDefaults.
So, let's dive in here.
First thing you need
to use UserDefaults is,
you need an instance of UserDefaults,
all the methods functions
that you're gonna use
in UserDefaults are instance methods.
So, we do that usually by this static var
called standard on UserDefaults.
Already kinda weird, right?
So you say UserDefaults dot standard,
and you get this shared
instance you can use
in your entire app.
Now, you can make other instances,
but this is, 99% of time,
how we do it.
And then, if we wanna store data,
we're gonna use this
function called set forKey.
And set takes the first
argument there, which is object,
that object has to be a property list.
So it has to be an Int or Array of Strings
or something that has only
those things we talked about
that could be in a property list.
But it can be anything,
as long as that's all that's in there.
And then forKey is just some
random String, and again,
this is like a Dictionary,
so that's the key to look it up later.
Now, for convenience, there's
also things like setDouble,
which takes a double forKey.
It's syntactic sugar really,
it's no different than
saying set with 37.5,
forKey is the same thing.
But you can see how this looks
like a Dictionary, right?
Setting values for a certain key.
Now how do I get the data back out?
Really easy.
There's a whole bunch of
functions like integer forKey,
data forKey, URL forKey,
even String Array forKey,
where it will go look in
UserDefaults, at that key,
see what anyone has stored there before,
and if it's able to make
it into the type you want,
like a URL or a String
Array, it will return it.
If not, it's going to return nil.
So this is great if it's
one of those basic types,
but what if you have an Array
of something besides Strings?
Well, it starts to get complicated,
and this is where Any starts to come out
in, a monster to get us.
And so, if I try to store
an Array of, let's say,
Dictionaries, that's legal,
but there's no function called
give me the Array of Dictionaries,
there's only Array of String,
that's only Array one there is.
So if you call just Array forKey,
you're gonna get an Array of Any.
And, how do I deal with this Any?
Well, you're gonna have to
use this operator in Swift
called as to typecast
the things in the Array
from Any's to being what
type you hopefully know
what they are.
We're gonna stop right here.
I don't wanna really talk
about typecasting and all that,
you really don't need to
do that very much in Swift.
Now, your reading assignment this week
is going to talk about that,
so if you wanna know about this,
you'll see the section called typecasting,
it'll tell you all about it.
And hopefully though, you can
just avoid this whole thing
by somehow figuring how to
use one of these normal ones
from the top of the screen right here,
and Codable might really help you there,
because then you can use data forKey.
And Codable can help you
turn almost any struct,
even an Array of some
wacky thing, into a Data.
That's all I'm gonna say
about UserDefaults for today.
And we're gonna get onto
our main topic here,
which is gesture.
So gestures is really about
getting input from the user.
We call this multitouch
because, of course,
you can put multiple fingers
down at the same time,
and do gestures and SwiftUI
will recognize them.
Swift pretty much takes care
of recognizing these gestures
when someone puts two fingers down
and start squeezing
their fingers together,
Swift recognizes, whoa, that's
a pinch, they're pinching,
I know that gesture.
So it recognizes them,
all you have to do is say
which Views you want to
recognize which things,
and it'll start recognizing them.
But, it's not just
recognizing them that matters,
once it recognizes that
this pinch is happening,
you and your code have
to handle the gesture.
So there's recognizing
it, Swift does that,
SwiftUI does that, and
then there's handling it,
which is something you have to do.
And handling it just
means deciding what to do
when there's a pinch or a drag or a tap.
So, let's talk first about how
you make your Views recognize
that a certain gesture is happening
using SwiftUI's powerful
gesture recognition.
And it's so simple, there is
just a ViewModifier on View
called .gesture, and
you just pass a Gesture.
This argument that you pass, a Gesture,
just needs to be anything
that implements the Gesture protocol,
and we're gonna talk about
what things implement the
Gesture protocol, and that's it.
And then after that,
your myView right there,
whenever that gesture starts
to happen in your View,
you're going to be asked to handle it.
Now how do we create this Gesture?
How do we specify what
gesture we want here?
We almost always do that with
either a func in our View,
or maybe it's a computed var,
or it even could be a local
var at the top of our body var,
right before we do it.
Anywhere you can store this thing is fine,
and this computer var or func or whatever
just has to return something
that is some Gesture.
So you know what some means,
it means you can return
anything you want in there
as long as it implements that protocol,
and Swift will figure out
that return type for you.
So right here I have var theGesture,
and I'm returning TapGesture count of two.
Swift will know that some
gesture there is TapGesture.
This TapGesture is one of the gestures
that's built into SwiftUI.
You know it well, TapGesture.
This particular one here,
I've made with a count of two.
So this is actually a double tap.
TapGesture has an argument
to its initializer,
which is how many taps,
and my default is one,
but here I've said two.
With a combination of two
things of code you see on here,
the one at the top, and the one at bottom,
Swift will start recognizing a double tap.
But, it won't do anything
when the double tap happens,
'cause we haven't told Swift how to handle
a double tap happening.
So the next step we need
to do is to explain to it
how to handle, and it depends
on the kind of gestures,
how to do this.
So, some gestures are
discrete, like TapGesture,
and LongPressGesture can be discrete,
where it just, the tap happens,
and then go do something.
A LongPressGesture happens,
That's different than a pinch or a drag,
which, they're happening overtime,
we might wanna get involved in that.
So for discrete gestures, those are easy,
let's get those out of the way.
You do something by calling
the function on your gesture
.onEnded, which takes a closure,
and in that closure you
do whatever you want
when that TapGesture ends.
Which means when the finger
comes back up for a tap,
or, if this is double tap,
the second time the finger comes back up.
And that's it.
Couldn't be easier to
handle a discrete gesture.
And of course, discrete gestures
are so simple and easy to handle,
they have these nice
convenience functions,
you've seen it on TapGesture.
I don't know if you know
that it takes the argument
count too, it does.
And then you just do something.
So that's exactly the same
thing as what we've seen
in the previous two slides.
Here we're just going
to handle a TapGesture.
So, discrete gestures, easy.
Non-discrete gestures, little more work.
In a non-discrete gesture,
you do get to handle when it ends,
which we'll talk about in a second,
just like a discrete gesture.
But you can also handle as it's moving,
as the fingers are pinching together,
or as they're rotating around,
or as the finger is dragging
itself around the screen,
you get to go do something,
redraw your View a whole bunch
of times as it moves around,
whatever you wanna do, you get to do it.
Now, examples of these
non-discrete gestures,
DragGesture, MagnificationGesture,
that's like a pinch,
RotationGesture, that's
like you're turning a dial
with two fingers, put two
fingers on the screen,
it's like turning a dial and
you're specifying some angle,
actually, that changes as you do that.
and even LongPressGesture
can kind of be non-discrete,
where you press and hold,
and so it's going to say
that the finger is holding,
and then when it comes back up
you'll find out it came up.
That's different from a tap.
You don't find out when the tap goes down,
you only find when it goes up,
but a long press, you can find out.
So, let's start by talking
about the end of them.
So, just like discrete,
we can find out the end,
and it's exactly the same .onEnded.
The only difference is,
the function that you pass,
the closure gets an argument.
Because, when a DragGesture ends,
you wanna find out, well, what
happened during that drag?
And so, you're gonna get
a little argument here,
this value argument,
and it's different for
every kind of Gesture,
and that is going to
tell you what happened.
For a DragGesture, the value is a struct
with things like the
starting position of the drag
and the ending position of the finger.
For magnification, it's the
scale of the magnification,
which is how far the fingers are apart
when they lifted up off the screen.
And the RotationGesture, similar, right.
It's like turning a
dial, so it's gonna say
how much angle did it turn
before the fingers lifted up?
Still get to ended, but you
get to find out, of course,
what happens there.
But the more interesting thing is,
during a non-discrete gesture,
you wanna find out as things are changing.
We do this by having some state
that is only going to be in effect
while the Gesture is going on.
This state is stored in any var you want,
you just have to mark it
with this special marker, @GestureState
And you must also give
this var an initial value
of some sort.
This var can be any type you want.
It could be a CGFloat,
it could be a struct
with all kinds of your own stuff in it.
There's no limit on what this var can be.
And what this var is basically going to do
is tell your View, here's all
the things you need to know
to draw yourself in the
middle of this Gesture.
That's what's going on here.
That's what this var is all about.
But it is marked specially,
and we're gonna talk about
what's special about it.
The first thing to understand
that's special about this var
is that it's always gonna
return to that starting value
when the Gesture ends.
That's why you must give
it a starting value.
So while the Gesture is going on,
you're going to be updating
this GestureState of yours
to reflect what's going on in the Gesture
every time the fingers move.
But as soon as the
fingers go up and it ends,
this is gonna get reset
back to starting value.
So you have to understand
that this @GestureState
is only the state while
the Gesture is active.
Very important to understand.
That's why I put this in red,
when the Gesture ends, it goes
back to the starting value.
Now, while the Gesture is happening,
you are given the opportunity, of course,
to change this state.
It's your own state, your own type,
so you're the one who has to change it.
And here's how you do that.
Just like you had .onEnded,
you have another function
on your DragGesture called .updating.
Now there's a lot of
colors on the screen here,
so let's go through all these
different colors we have.
The updating function takes two arguments,
and the first one in parentheses there is
your GestureState var.
So you're gonna pass your
GestureState var to .updating.
Notice that you have to put
a dollar in the front of it,
I'll talk a little bit about
that in the demo, why that is,
but really, we're not gonna
talk about this until next week.
But just always put a dollar
in front of your @GestureState var.
Just like .onEnded,
.updating takes a closure
that it's gonna call.
Now, it's gonna call that thing repeatedly
as the fingers are moving closer together,
or the fingers dragging across
the screen, or whatever,
it's gonna be calling this
closure over and over and over.
So what are the three
arguments we have there
to the closure?
The first one, that blue value argument,
that's the same thing is .onEnded.
That is, the state of this Gesture.
How close the fingers are
together for pinching,
how far they finger has moved
if we're dragging, whatever.
It's a struct.
It depends on which Gesture
we're talking about here
as to what's in there.
Might not be a struct, like magnification
I think it's just a CGFloat with a scale.
But for DragGestures, it's a struct,
with start location, end
location, timestamps,
other things in there.
So that's what that value is.
You're used to that, same as .onEnded.
The myGestureState purple argument there,
is essentially your @GestureState again.
And not only is it there,
it's also inside this little closure.
And you can assign it a value in there.
So, I'm gonna talk in
the demo briefly about
what's going on here, that's
essentially an inout parameter,
but all you really need to know
for the purposes of making this work,
is that your @GestureState variable
appears in these three places
as the argument to .updating,
as the second argument to the closure,
and then inside as a
changeable writable var
that you can change.
Now, if you wanna just put
your hands over your eyes
and not think about it,
you can just think that
inside this closure
you can change your @GestureState var.
That's not actually what's
happening, but it feels like it.
But the conceptual semantic
thing that's going on here,
in fact, is that this is the only way
you're supposed to change
your @GestureState.
You cannot change your
myGestureState any other place
except for right inside this closure.
And that makes sense,
because this @GestureState
is only supposed to be active
when the Gesture is going on.
So you would never wanna
set it at any other time.
There's actually no reason
to set it any other time
then while this thing's going on,
'cause that's all the @GestureState is.
Very important to understand,
this is the only place you
change your @GestureState var.
And you can change it
to anything you want,
and you're almost always going
to change it to something
based on what that blue value is, right.
Depending on how close
the fingers are together,
how much they've moved.
You're gonna update your
little @GestureState struct
so that your View draws itself properly
in the middle of a drag or a pinch.
Now, the third argument
there, transaction,
has to do with animation.
We're not gonna talk
about that in this course.
There are some limits,
we just don't have time
to talk about everything.
You can look at the documentation
if you wanna try and
figure out transaction.
It's for advanced animation
interactions between Views,
we just have to draw the line somewhere.
Now, there is actually
simpler version of .updating,
it's called .onChanged.
And, when you first see
this you might be like,
oh this is simpler, I'm gonna use this,
but it's only for
certain kinds of changes.
And I'll explain that in a second.
So, .onChanged looks just like .updating,
except for, there's
not that @GestureState.
Because in the .onChanged,
you don't get to update any @GestureState.
This value is passed to you,
and you just have to do
something based on it.
And that's why it's
quite limited to do this.
But, there are some kinds
of things that you can do,
and what are those things?
Well, if you were doing something where
you're actually interested in
the actual finger positions,
like you're doing, drag to select, right,
you're dragging your
finger across the screen
to select objects or something like that,
then you just wanna know where
that drag out is right now.
That's different then if you're pinching
to scale something up or down,
or moving something around,
or whatever, relative
to where it was before.
It's like absolute finger position, or,
you're gonna follow the finger
around and draw like a pen
in your app or something.
Then you might want this.
But, most of the time you're interested
in the relative change.
How much you've pinched down?
How far you've dragged across screen?
And when you're interested
in relative changes,
that's when you need .updating.
All right, so I'm gonna summarize
all the things I just
said here in one slide.
So this is a chance for you to review
and get it all at once.
So here's how we handle
non-discrete gestures
when the fingers are moving.
First, we're gonna collect
any information that we need
to draw our View while
the gesture's happening
into a @GestureState var.
Might only just be a CGFloat,
might be a whole struct.
Then, we're gonna add
.updating to our Gesture.
Whatever our pinch or drag is.
And inside the .updating
closure that we passed,
we're gonna get the value
of what's going on with
the Gesture, repeatedly.
It's gonna constantly call
us with the latest value
of what's going on.
We are going to update our @GestureState,
but we're gonna understand
that that @GestureState,
when the thing ends, is gonna go away.
And go back to its starting value.
So, in .onEnded of a non-discrete Gesture,
we're gonna be sure to update
whatever we need to do,
so that when that thing goes
back to its starting value,
our View still draws properly.
All right, so let's hop into the demo.
I'm gonna show you that
Codable thing I talked about.
We're gonna use UserDefaults
to store our document,
because I didn't have time so far
to teach you about the
file system and all that.
There's quite a bit involved there,
so we'll do that later.
I'm gonna do some other
cool stuff, animating fonts,
but mostly what we're gonna
do today is do some gestures
in our EmojiArt,
make it so we can make our
document bigger and smaller,
and pan around in it, that kinda stuff.
All right, let's continue
to improve our EmojiArt.
And it has a big problem, currently.
For example, if start building
a really beautiful EmojiArt,
some apples at the base of our tree,
and then, I quit my app, when I come back,
I've lost all the work that I've done.
So, that's not good.
Next week or the week after,
we'll actually work on
having multiple documents,
and a document chooser, and all that.
But today, let's just try and work on
making our document persist.
When we make something
persist, what do we need?
Kinda need two things.
One, need some sort of
file format to store it in.
And then we need a place to put it.
Probably the place
we're gonna wanna put it
is in the file system,
and I'm hoping to get
around to showing you that
in a couple of weeks.
But, in the meantime,
we're just gonna put it in UserDefaults,
which we talked about in the slides today.
Now, UserDefaults is
totally the wrong place
to put a document, but it's a really easy,
one line of code, bam,
it's in the UserDefaults.
And really, what we're focused on here,
is not where we're storing it, but more,
what file format are we gonna use,
and how do we generate that file format.
And the file format
we're gonna use is JSON.
So, most of you probably
have heard of JSON before.
It's a file format that's used,
mostly to pass things
around on the Internet.
It's a public file format.
And iOS has awesome feature built in
where it will generate JSON
from almost any struct
that you can imagine.
So, we have our EmojiArtDocument
as a struct in our Model,
and we can use this cool iOS feature
to generate a JSON version of it.
So let's do that.
Let's hop back in here, go to
our Model, here's our Model.
And we just wanna turn
this whole thing here
into a blob of JSON.
So how do we do that?
I'm going to have a var called json.
It's gonna return a Data.
Now, this Data is just a bag of bits.
In our case, it's going
to have JSON in there.
So I'm just gonna return
trying to use a JSONEncoder
to encode myself.
This is the only line
of code we really need
to generate a JSON version of ourself.
But you can see we have an error here.
It says instance method encode
requires that EmojiArt
conform to Encodable.
All right, so, this is
functional programming,
of course there's a protocol
involved, Encodable.
So, our EmojiArt, essentially,
Encodable has to be
something it conforms to.
And, amazingly, because
of extensions, again,
that are in Swift, usually
you could just put Encodable
on a struct and it'll just work.
But, this one doesn't quite work.
And, it's gonna work or not,
depending on whether each var
that's in your struct is itself Encodable.
So let's look at our vars.
We got the background URL.
URL, definitely that's Encodable,
I can guarantee you that.
Emojis, what type is it?
It's an Array.
Arrays, definitely Encodable.
But what's in the Array?
Emoji.
Oh, that's this struct.
Ah, okay, this struct is not Encodable.
No problem, we'll just
say Encodable, and again,
using the same mechanism,
Swift has automatically made it Encodable,
and now everything in my
EmojiArt is Encodable.
So, it's Encodable, and
everything in this Emoji struct
is also Encodable.
Strings, Ints, those are Encodable.
So, this is Encodable.
Now, we almost never
make a struct Encodable
without also being Decodable.
It's no use turning something into a JSON
if you can't turn it back
into one of these things.
And we'll make both of
these Decodable, of course.
It's so common, in fact,
to have both Encodable and Decodable.
Now there's another protocol
that inherits both of them
which is Codable.
So this is the protocol
we're gonna specify
when we wanna make something
be turnable into JSON.
So nothing more is required
in making this Codable.
If you have a struct
that doesn't have standard types like this
or sub structs that can be marked Codable,
Codable is a protocol,
it's got functions in
there that you can use
to turn anything into an encoded thing
that can be JSON-ized.
But, most of the time, we
try to use simple types
that we can do it on.
So, it's not really within the realm,
we're only in week four of this class,
and not really in our knowledge base yet
to go off and make something Codable
that doesn't use standard types,
but you know where to start.
You can go look at this protocol,
see what the description of it is,
and, if you ever needed to,
you could make your own structs Codable,
even if they weren't using
these standard types.
So now we have the JSON,
I wanna look at this,
I wanna see this JSON.
So what I'm gonna do, actually,
is go back to my document,
and every time I change my EmojiArt,
I'm gonna print out on the console
a JSON representation of it.
When I say every time this changes,
some of you are thinking oh
yeah, we know how to do that,
didSet right, this is a property observer.
This is gonna get called every
time EmojiArt gets changed.
Unfortunately, there's a
bug in Swift right now,
and if you're watching this
after the Stanford quarter is over,
it's quite possible that this
bug has been fixed in Swift.
But during the Stanford
quarter, it's not yet fixed.
And the problem is that property wrappers,
which is what this @Published is,
and @State is also a
property wrapper, et cetera.
These don't play well currently
with property observers.
That's a known problem
that's gonna get fixed soon,
at least I hope.
But it keeps us from
doing this nice thing,
where in here we could just say print
the JSON version of my EmojiArt equals,
and here I'll just say emojiArt.json.
And this JSON is a data, of
course, an Optional data,
and I wanna turn it into a UTF-8 String.
So UTF-8 is a String in
coding that JSON always uses.
And since this might be nil, if it's nil,
then return the String nil.
This utf8 var is something
that I added to data
in the EmojiArt extension,
so you can check that out.
So, it would be nice if we
could just have this print out
every time this changes.
Since these two aren't
compatible, what we're gonna do
is stop having this be @Published,
we're gonna take that out of there.
And we're even gonna
mark here that this is
a workaround for property observer problem
with property wrappers.
And instead, we still need this EmojiArt
when it's going to change to
do the ObservableObject thing.
And this is a good
reminder what that's doing,
and I'm gonna do it in my willSet,
objectWillChange.send.
That's what this
ObservableObject thing is doing
when we're Published, its publishing this
something changed message.
So we mentioned that way back when
we first talked about ObervableObject,
but just as reminder.
So I'm doing that myself,
now this is not quite as good
as having this being published.
We really haven't learned
enough about @Publish
and what it's doing to understand
why this is not quite as good.
It's gonna work for
our purposes just fine,
but @Publish, actually
is providing something
called a publisher for
this thing changing,
and we can use that.
In fact, if we knew more about published
at this point in the quarter,
we could use it to do this
workaround in a different way
that would probably be a little better.
But this is fine, this
makes it work for us.
We're still going to have
our ObservableObject notice changes,
and we're gonna print
out JSON on every time
our EmojiArt changes.
Let's take a look, see if that worked.
And I'm gonna drag something,
now, as soon as I drop this,
I believe my EmojiArt should
change and I should see JSON.
Ready?
Boom, woo hoo, we did.
In fact, let's make this smaller,
we can see it going at the same time.
There's our JSON down here,
it's got the background image.
Let's see the emojis.
No emojis 'cause I
haven't put any emojis in.
Let's go and put an emoji in.
Maybe an apple below the tree again.
There is an apple.
How about maybe planet Earth
up in the sky up there?
Or Mars or something here?
And you can see that it is generating JSON
that represents our whole document.
So that was super easy
to be able to generate JSON like that.
And now, we're going to do
another super easy thing is,
we're gonna throw that
JSON into UserDefaults
as a way of making our document permanent.
Now, again, we don't have
multiple documents yet,
we can't name documents,
we really should be putting
them in the file system
or even in iCloud or something
like that, but for now,
let's just make it persist
so that when we quit,
and then we go back, we don't
lose our beautiful images.
Now how're we gonna do that?
So I'm gonna stop printing here,
I'm just gonna say UserDefault.standard,
that's the standard UserDefaults database.
You can have others, but
that's the standard one,
we use that 99% of the time.
Set this EmojiArt JSON
value for a certain key,
and you'll remember that from the slides,
that UserDefaults is like a Dictionary,
feels like a Dictionary.
Now you just have to specify a key,
I'll say EmojiArtDocument dot,
this is like an untitled
document or something.
This key can be anything,
we tend to put something
like the class name
or the struct name at the beginning of it,
just because this UserDefaults standard
is used for a whole app,
we might have other structs
that wanna be storing things
in UserDefaults, and we
don't want their keys
to collide with ours.
And that's it, that's going
to write this thing in there.
Notice this is a Data,
and it knows that, this UserDefaults
knows how to put in Datas,
and Strings, and Dates,
and Ints, and Floats,
and Arrays of those things,
and Dictionaries of those things.
And that's it.
It also knows how to handle an Optional,
because this is an Optional.
If I say set, and this is nil,
it'll just clear out
anything for this key.
Now, we wanna get it out.
How do we get that thing out?
Well, back in our EmojiArt,
we know how to encode ourself as a JSON.
But we need some code over
here to decode ourself.
Let me do that with an init.
I'm gonna have an init
that takes a JSON Data as an argument,
and tries to look at
this Data and decode it
to be an EmojiArt.
So, how would we do that?
I'm just gonna say if this JSON
Data does not equal to nil,
I obviously can't decode nil,
then I'm going to let a new
EmojiArt that I'm gonna create
equal trying to use a JSONDecoder
to decode an EmojiArt.
And here I'm specifying the
type of thing I want to decode,
and when we specify type, remember,
we put .self like URL.self we
did for the drop last time.
And I'm gonna do this from
the JSON that was passed in.
And this is either gonna work or not.
It also has a try, just
like this had a try,
and the Data contentsOf had a try.
If just fails, it's gonna return nil.
So this if let is just gonna do nothing,
or we won't get in here.
But if this doesn't fail,
now I have a new EmojiArt.
So now I kinda wanna replace my whole self
with this new EmojiArt, 'cause
I'm initializing myself,
and believe it or not, for
a value type you can say,
self equals something.
You are allowed, with a value type,
to assign something to self,
and it'll replace the whole thing.
Can do it with enums too.
And that's great, that's
exactly what I want.
I'm initializing.
I'm just gonna set myself
equal to whatever EmojiArt
I was able to decode from
the JSON that you gave me.
But, what if I can't decode it though?
If I don't do anything here,
I'm gonna get a blank EmojiArtDocument.
'Cause I won't have
initialized any of these
to something different
than their defaults, which,
this one is nil, and
this is an empty Array,
so I'd get a blank EmojiArtDocument.
But, I don't think
that's what I want here.
If someone asked me to create
an EmojiArtDocument with JSON,
and I'm unable to do it for some reason,
I really need to let them know.
And, the way I'm gonna do that
is with a failable initializer.
If you put question mark right after init,
then when people call this initializer,
if this initializer returns nil,
then they'll get nil back as the object
they were trying to create.
And that really is gonna send the message,
I tried to create EmojiArt
with the JSON, but I couldn't.
So a failable initializer, really easy,
you just put question,
return nil whenever you fail,
and then people are creating you,
they have to check for nil,
because you're returning, essentially,
an Optional version of EmojiArt here.
Now we added an init here,
and I don't know if
you remember the rules?
But if you add an init, then
you lose your free init,
the free init that
specifies each argument.
These all have defaults,
so you could say init with no arguments,
which is what we do over here, actually,
we created an EmojiArt
empty with no arguments.
We lost that init, so
we have to add it back.
So, an init with no arguments
does nothing in our structs,
it just takes these default
values and uses them.
So now we have a way of
creating an EmojiArtDocument
from this JSON data, so
let's use that over here.
Instead of doing this, where
we create an empty one,
I'm going to have an init for my document.
And in my init, I'm just
gonna set my EmojiArt equal to
the EmojiArt that I get
from passing the JSON
that I get out of UserDefaults.
So I'm gonna use my standard UserDefaults,
this time I'm gonna ask for
a Data for that same key.
Now, I could just copy and
paste this down to here,
but that's a dangerous move,
if I miss a character or
whatever, then these won't match.
So let's be good programmers and instead,
create a little static var.
I'm gonna call it untitled.
Lets make it private static let
untitled equals that String,
and then I'll use that down here,
EmojiArtDocument.untitled.
This way I'm guaranteed
that whatever I'm saving out
is the same key I'm
using to get it back in.
By the way, once we load
this EmojiArt back up,
we're for sure going to want
to fetch our background image,
because your EmojiArtDocument
doesn't store the image,
just the URL.
So we gotta go back out on the Internet
and get the image data when we load it up.
Now we're still having an error here,
value of Optional type EmojiArt,
EmojiArt Optional must be
unwrapped to a type EmojiArt.
And that makes sense, right?
Because this is a failable
initializer, it could return nil.
EmojiArt up here can't take nil,
it's not an Optional EmojiArt.
So what I'm gonna do here
is, if it returns nil,
I'm gonna create a blank document.
So at least we have some document.
Okay, let's fire this thing up.
Let's see if it works.
Okay, we start out with a
blank document, of course,
that's this question mark
question mark blank document
because we couldn't load
anything up from UserDefaults
at the start, there was nothing in there.
But if we start building our
thing here, let's do that.
Put our apples back in here.
Put our Earth up in the sky up here.
This is hopefully writing
out the JSON as we speak
to our UserDefaults.
Let's quit, and then run it
again and see what happens.
Woo hoo, there's our document.
Now, sometimes you have
to be a little careful.
If we, I don't know, drop a
baseball in the front yard,
there it is, and now we press
stop, and then we run again,
oh, we lost her baseball.
Why didn't the baseball work?
Well, UserDefaults, when you
put things in UserDefaults,
it doesn't run right out to
the disk and write it out,
it buffers them up and writes them out
at an appropriate time,
when it's convenient.
And, we don't give it a chance to do that
because we picked this baseball
up, we put it down here,
and we hit stop, and that kills our app.
It just kills it.
There's no chance to go
do something like that.
So when you're doing
debugging and you're using,
we got lucky that time, it wrote it out.
When you're doing that,
one thing you wanna do is,
when you have a change
and you want UserDefaults
to write things out, just
switch to another app.
Here I'm gonna switch to the files app.
Doesn't really matter, and switch back.
Because when you switch to another app,
UserDefaults is always gonna
write the database out.
That way when you quit, and
you come back, it's there.
That's all I really wanted to talk about
in terms of storage for now,
and we're gonna be working on this more
as the quarter goes on.
But the next thing I wanna
talk about is gestures.
What I wanna be able to do
here is to zoom in and out
on my document.
And I'll show you why.
Here's another image down here.
Let's go ahead and drag
and drop this image in here
and see what happens.
Whoa.
Okay, it definitely put that
image in here, but it's huge.
This is just a huge image.
And so, I really want to
be able to zoom in here.
I'm holding down option by
the way, in the simulator,
that's how you can simulate
two fingers being down.
And I really wanna zoom in and
see the whole picture here.
There's another horse, whole
bunch of other animals,
I wanna be able to see these things.
Now, I don't know if you know this,
another terrible problem
with this huge image,
it blasted our emoji palette.
We can't even add more emojis,
they all got wiped out up here.
This is somehow drawing outside
of where it's supposed to draw.
And that's actually normal in SwiftUI.
The default in SwiftUI is for Views
to be able to draw outside
of their boundaries.
So if we wanna keep a View
inside its boundaries,
we have to do a modifier on it.
So let's start with that,
let's get our pallet back
before we do anything.
The modifier we use,
really, really simple.
Gonna put it, let's put it
on the ZStack right here.
So here's our ZStack of stuff.
It's called .clipped
.clipped just means
all the drawing it does
is gonna be clipped to
the bounds of the View.
By the way, while I'm here,
let's move this stuff,
the edges stuff, and the dropping stuff,
let's move that down here as well.
Reason I'm moving that out here is,
these do semantically apply to the ZStack,
we do want the ZStack going
all the way to the edges,
and we wanna be able to
drop anywhere in the ZStack.
And it cleans up this in here
so it's much cleaner of
what's going on in here.
Although, this is not
very clean right here.
Let's go make sure this clipped worked,
then we're gonna run back in here
and fix this not so
clean code right there.
All right, here's our big thing.
And it's still big, so we
still need our gesture,
but look, woo, we still
have our various emoji
and we can still drop them in there.
All right, let's go
back and clean that code
I was talking about.
This code, why is this not really clean?
In SwiftUI, it's all really
about breaking these Views down
into small little Views.
Especially when you have a
semantic boundary of a View
like we have here.
What is this code all about?
This code is all just about
showing this background image,
but unfortunately it might be nil,
so we have to check for that.
That's all we're doing here.
And, if someone's
reading through our code,
they're having to pass a lot of code here
just to realize that
we're showing an image
that might be Optional.
We shouldn't ask readers of our code
to have this much trouble
understanding what's going on.
I'm gonna make another sub-View,
and this is the way we break this down.
We just make, either
called functions and vars
to put our View somewhere else,
or we can make new Views,
like we made CardView.
So I'm gonna make another
View down here, I'm gonna say
struct. I'm gonna call it OptionalImage.
And it's just gonna be
a View that takes a var,
which is a UIImage, Optional UIImage.
And then my var body is gonna
return some View, as always.
I'm just gonna put this code in there,
so I'm gonna go grab this code,
let's get this outta here.
Cut, just down in here, paste.
Of course, I'm using this uiImage
instead of this backgroundImage.
That's it.
So I've just created this
little utility thing right here,
and all it does is handle a
UIImage that might be nil.
And now, my code up here
turns from all that mess
to just OptionalImage of a
self.document.backgroundImage.
Much cleaner up here to
understand what's going on.
Especially looking at
this ZStack right here,
it's clear that this
is my background image
and these are my emojis.
Much simpler.
Now this OptionalImage,
this has nothing to do
with EmojiArt, whatsoever.
So I'm gonna take it outta here
and put it in its own file.
Which, you really wanna do that,
when you have something that's unrelated,
don't bury those things
inside unrelated code.
So this is called OptionalImage,
put in its own file.
And this file that I've
created right here,
I might well use this,
pick it up and drag it into
some other app that I'm writing,
it's quite a useful little View here,
and quite reusable in that sense.
Wanted to take that little detour,
just because I didn't want
you to be creating these Views
that just had hundreds
of lines of code in here,
and then just completely
un-understandable.
Okay, back to what we wanna do which is,
we want to be able to, in
our EmojiArt over here,
zoom in on these huge images so we can see
what's going on there.
We're gonna do that by
introducing a new piece of @State
into our View, which I'm
gonna call our zoomScale.
This is just @State because
it's only going to affect
the way our View looks.
This has nothing to do with
our EmojiArt document itself,
it's purely a UI visual
thing, and it's temporary.
As we zoom in and out,
it's just showing us how
much zooming there is.
It's just gonna be a CGFloat.
I'm gonna start out equal 1.0.
And this is room scale is gonna be
how much were zoomed in or
out on our entire document.
zoomScale 1.0 means our document is
whatever the size of its
background URL's image is.
But 2.0 means it's twice as big as that.
And .5 means it's half as big as that.
The first thing I'm gonna
do with this zoomScale
is go apply it to everywhere in my View
where it would matter.
So, for example, my background
image, clearly that matters,
I want to scaleEffect
it to be our zoomScale.
So that's gonna make my
background image the right size.
Of course, my emojis here
also need to get bigger
when I zoom in.
So that's their font.
So let's go down to
their font, here it is.
We're seeing their font to this font size,
we gotta zoom that up by our zoomScale.
And the other thing we need to do is
every time we're converting
from this iOS coordinate system,
which is (0, 0) in the upper left,
to the EmojiArt coordinate system,
which is (0, 0) in the middle,
we have to be careful because
when things are far away from the middle,
when they're zoomed up, they're
very far from the middle,
so it effects that.
So where are the two
places that we convert
those coordinate systems?
One is here when we're dropping.
And also here where we're
positioning the emojis,
this place where we're
going through the emojis
and putting them down.
Well, obviously we're
being told where they are
in EmojiArt's (0, 0)
centered coordinate system,
we need to convert them.
So we need to fix both of these cases.
Our location of the drop
is now just going to be
the location it was, but
divided by the zoomScale.
Same thing with y.
So that fixes
the coordinate system
transformation for drops.
And for position, kinda
have this embedded here,
let's clean this up a little bit,
I'm gonna say my location
is my emoji's location,
and I'm gonna modify the
location to be this essentially,
except for that.
Now I put it in location.
I'm gonna return that location
and by splitting that out,
it makes it really easy for us to add this
little zoomScale modification
to it right before.
So I'm gonna say
location equals CGPoint
location.x times our zoomScale,
and the y is location.y
times our zoomScale.
That seems to be all the places I think
that our zoomScale would apply.
We're zooming our document in nicely.
What gesture are we gonna use?
Well, we wanna pinch.
But I'm gonna have another
gesture that's kinda fun,
which is double tap.
And double tap is going
to zoom my entire document
to exactly fit the space available.
We get a certain amount
of space for our document,
depending on where our app is in the UI,
and I'm gonna zoom it to fit that.
So let's create a new private func here,
that I'm gonna call zoomToFit.
And it's gonna take the
image to have it fit.
Might be nil 'cause our
background image can be nil,
in some size.
And it's just going to set our zoomScale.
It's gonna set the zoomScale to fit.
Now, I'm only gonna do
this if we have an image.
We have an image, I'm not
gonna touch the zoomScale,
and I'm also only gonna do this
if that image has some size,
so I'm gonna check to make sure
that the image.size.width
is greater than zero,
and that the image.size.height
is greater than zero.
So, we have some image of some size
and now we're going to zoomToFit it.
Now we could zoom it based
on the horizontal zoom
by saying size.width divided
by images.size.width.
Or we could do it by the vertical zooming,
which would be the size.height divided by
the image.size.height.
So which of these two should we use,
the horizontal or the vertical?
I think we're gonna use
the smaller of the two.
So I'm gonna set my zoomScale
equal to the min of the horizontal zoom
or the vertical zoom.
So whichever is gonna make it smaller.
That way the image will
always be fully on screen
no matter what.
Almost there.
Now we just need to add to
the gesture to our Views.
We just need to mark whichever Views
we want that double tap to work on,
to be able to do this.
So I'm gonna make it
so that double tapping on the
background here does that.
So let's go here and add a gesture.
We do that with the gesture ViewModifier,
and we just specify the gesture we want.
Now I'm going to make a little function
to make that gesture
called doubleTapToZoom in geometry.size.
And this function has to return
something that is some Gesture.
This gesture only takes a
Gesture as its argument.
So I'm gonna go down here
and create a private func
called doubleTapToZoom in size.
And it has to return some Gesture.
That's what this ViewModifier
takes, it takes some Gesture.
So we have to return some Gesture.
What Gesture are we gonna return?
Well, we're doing double tap,
so that is a TapGesture.
There are a number of Gestures,
we talked about this in the slides.
TapGesture is a good one doing double tap.
In fact, I want a TapGesture
whose count is two.
And I'm gonna return that.
But of course, I have to specify,
when this TapGesture
happens, what am I gonna do?
In this case I wanna call zoomToFit.
We do that by the .onEnded
function in Gesture.
Now .onEnded takes a function to execute
when this Gesture, whatever it is,
in this case a double tap, ends.
So a double tap is when that
second tap finger comes up,
it ended, and we can do .onEnded here.
What are we gonna do in here?
self.zoomToFit.
And what are we gonna fit?
We're gonna fit our
document's backgroundImage.
And the size is the
size that was passed in.
So let's take a look.
Here's our huge image.
I'm gonna double tap.
Woo, we made it small.
Let's go for the smaller
image, this little guy.
It's a really small image,
'cause we're zoomed in right now.
(vocalizing)
Now the only thing I don't really like
about what I've done here is it's jarring.
And we know that in
mobile apps we want things
not to jump like that.
We want some animation.
So let's throw some animation in here.
You know how to do that,
with animation, explicit animation.
With the zoomToFit in there.
Let's see how that works.
Woo, that looks a lot lot better.
But, I actually think I
notice something weird
with the emojis there.
So let's go get the small one here.
And watch these emojis.
Ooh, they're kinda jerky.
Anytime I see in an animation
I don't really like what I'm seeing,
I'm gonna go over here
and slow it way down.
Let's use a linear animation here.
Duration, let's say 4 seconds.
And let's just watch that thing in action.
All right, let's pick up the
bigger one again, here it is.
Right, now I'm gonna double tap.
And we're gonna watch these emoji.
Oh whoa, so the emoji aren't animating,
they just jumped to the
size they should be.
And actually, I think
it's even worse than that.
Let's go and watch them now going bigger,
ready, ready, watch here.
Oh, see that?
They went big and then they got cut off
because the size of
the View was animating,
but it hadn't caught
up to how big they are.
This is a problem.
We have to somehow animate
the size of this font
that's being used.
Well, we know how to do this.
This is a little bit of
review for you actually.
How does animation work in SwiftUI?
It happens with ViewModifiers.
Now, I'm not gonna go through,
we're already pressed
for time in this demo,
so I'm not gonna go
through all the details
of making our own Animatable
font size ViewModifier,
but I did do it.
So let's go over here and drag it in.
Here is my Animatable modifier.
I'm gonna take a brief look at this code.
You can look at it at your leisure later.
But all it's doing is
essentially making animatableData
that is the font size.
So I have this font size,
it's the animatableData,
and my content is just a Font,
the system font of that size.
Couldn't be easier.
I've even made a nice
little extension on View
that let's me be able to
say .font animatableWithSize
and give it the size, and it
will automatically modify it.
This is really easy to apply this.
Wherever we set the font,
which is right here,
instead of calling this
self set font for emoji,
which is down here,
I'm just gonna take this
size, cut it out of there,
not gonna need this anymore,
and put it right up in here
in my new font animatableWithSize.
There it is.
That's the size I want.
And we need self.
This is going to modify this
Text in an animatable way
to this new font size.
And again, can double tap here.
Okay, it's a little slow, it
looks like it's working there.
Let's make the really big one over here.
Okay, watching carefully now, here we go.
Ooh yeah, looking good.
Much smoother animation there.
And, the real test, try the smaller one.
Ooh, okay, so it looks like our animation
is working perfectly here.
Let's go ahead and speed it back up.
And move on to doing our pinch.
So the pinch is just a
different kind of gesture.
And you'll remember from the
slides that we did today,
that the way these
non-discrete gestures work,
like drags and pinches, is that
while the gesture's active,
we are going to modify some state,
and that state is going to
affect the way things look
while we're doing the pinch or the drag.
And then, when the drag ends,
whatever the end state is,
we are going to update
our steady state value
for whatever, modifying our View.
And it stays in that state.
The key to understanding
how these gestures work,
these non-discrete gestures is,
that you're gonna have two
different pieces of state.
So we're gonna have our state,
which is our zoomScale normally,
I'm gonna rename that
to steadyStateZoomScale.
So this is gonna be the
zoomScale that we have
just in steady state, not
while a gesture is going on.
And then we're gonna have
a new piece of state,
which is going to be @GestureState,
which is different than
@State, slightly different,
and it's going to be the gestureZoomScale.
So this is going to be the
zoomScale we're going to use
while the gesture is going on.
Now, it's important to know
that this @GestureState
could be of any type.
It doesn't actually even have
to be the same kind of thing
that your steady state one is doing.
This just has to be whatever
information is going to change
every time the pinch moves,
or a drag moves, or whatever,
that let's you keep track of it.
Now, in our case, when we're pinching,
we do just wanna keep track
of whatever the scale is.
So, that makes it so that our
zoomScale that we had before,
we're still gonna have that,
and it's gonna be computed
by just returning
the steadyStateZoomScale
times the gestureZoomScale.
Now this gestureZoomScale is 1.0,
so when a gesture's not going on,
it's just, this is gonna be equal right?
steadyStateZoomScale times 1.0
is gonna be the same as
steadyStateZoomScale.
But when our gesture's working,
and a pinch moves out a little bit,
it starts to be greater than one
and our zoomScale's gonna go up.
And when this pinch comes back
in, it's gonna go back lower.
So our job is to make a
gesture, a pinching gesture,
that modifies this gestureZoomScale
only while we are pinching.
And then, right at the end of the gesture,
it's going to update this
to our steadyState value.
And that's how we do gestures.
Now, notice down here
we're getting an error,
that's because the resuming to fit,
we obviously are trying to zoomToFit
our steadyStateZoomScale.
We make a gesture for
pinching exactly the same way
as we do this gesture for doubleTapToZoom.
We're just gonna have .gesture,
and we're gonna have a different function.
I'm gonna call this my zoomGesture.
And my zoomGesture actually
doesn't need the size,
it's not like double tap
where it needs the size.
So I have this zoomGesture.
By the way, this could be a var,
this doesn't have to be a func
since it doesn't take any arguments.
Let's go ahead and put
our zoomGesture down here.
Let's put it right in here,
private func zoomGesture.
And it's also gonna return some Gesture.
Because we're passing it to
this gesture function here,
it has to, some zoom Gesture.
Also, by the way, I think
I'm gonna put my zoomGesture
on the whole document.
So I'm just gonna put this down
here on the whole document,
not just on our background.
I don't think there's a difference
because our background, it
fills our entire document.
But again, more just for code clarity,
I'm going to separate these things out.
This zoomGesture returns some Gesture.
What kind of Gesture?
It's gonna return what's
called a MagnificationGesture,
that's how we do a pinch.
So it's just gonna return it.
And in fact, it's the
same as the double tap
in that has an .onEnded.
The only difference with the .onEnded
of a MagnificationGesture
is that it gives you,
as an argument, the finalGestureScale.
So this is the gestureScale
that was at the end
when the user's fingers
went up from the pinch.
Now with this finalGestureScale,
I can just reset my
steadyStateZoomScale to times equals
my finalGestureScale.
So if the gesture went to twice as big,
and the fingers went up,
now in my steady state,
I'm gonna be twice as big.
And same thing if it
went down to half as big.
So, the .onEnded, just
like the .onEnded down here
with double tap was easy to implement.
The trick, or the key parts
of doing these non-discrete gestures,
is while it's changing.
So here's what that looks like.
It's called .updating.
And .updating takes an
argument which is your,
whatever your @GestureState
is for this gesture.
So, we'll say gestureZoomScale.
However, you have to put
a dollar sign in front,
and we're gonna talk about
what this dollar sign means next week.
It turns this into
what's called a Binding.
So it is bound to this other var.
But, you really don't need to know that
to make this Gesture stuff at work.
Understand it's just
essentially linking up
to your @GestureState.
And, of course, this
takes an argument as well,
which is a function.
This function is called
every time the pinch gesture changes.
So this is constantly being called,
this little function is
constantly being called
as the pinch moves in and out.
And this thing has three arguments.
The first one, very easy to understand,
it's the latestGestureScale.
That's just telling you what
the latest pinch looked like.
The second argument is really weird.
It's our @GestureState
as an inout parameter,
we'll talk about that in a second.
And the last argument
here is a transaction.
I'm not gonna talk about transactions.
Transactions are essentially capturing
the animation environment
that this is all happening in.
That's a little bit of
advanced use for animation
that we're gonna pretty
much ignore in this class.
So, we're gonna ignore
this argument as well.
But we are gonna focus on
this ourGestureStateInOut.
So, an inout parameter,
hopefully you got this from
your reading assignment last week.
But, it takes an argument in normally,
so when something calls this function,
the argument comes in normally.
But then, if you actually
assign a value to this,
then it gets copied
back out on the way out.
So this gesture is
essentially passing you,
your own @GestureState var in,
letting you modify it in here.
And then when you pass it out,
it turns it up here and changes it.
So why is that happening?
Why are we not just changing
our gestureZoomScale
directly in here,
why am I not saying
gestureZoomScale equals something?
Why do I do it through this variable?
Well the answer for that is
that this @GestureState var,
while it's in your View, is
really owned by this Gesture.
Other than the initial
value that you give it,
you should never assign
a value to this directly.
Always let the Gesture handle it.
What does the Gesture
do with it, by the way?
Well, when the Gesture is not happening,
it leaves it at 1.0.
And then while the Gesture is happening,
it's passing it to you and
you can modify it here.
And then when it's over,
it goes back to 1.0.
So, the Gesture wants to own that var,
and so you are not allowed to own it.
This inout business,
if you don't really
understand what I'm saying
about inout parameters,
didn't understand the reading,
maybe go back and do the reading.
But even then if you don't understand it,
then just understand
that the Gesture here,
this MagnificationGesture
only wants you to modify
your @GestureState
inside this function
that's called repeatedly
as the pinch happens.
Now, because that's what this is doing,
a lot of people will rename
this to be the exact same name
as their @GestureState variable.
And when they do this, call
it the exact same thing,
now it kinda looks like you
are changing this in here.
I'm actually a fan of that,
I don't say this at the beginning,
because I want you to understand
what's happening here.
But, I think naming this
the same is a good idea.
So, what do we wanna do
every time that pinch goes in and out
or changes a little bit?
Well, here we just want to
grab the latestGestureScale.
So whatever this is, the
last time the pinch moved,
we want to set that as
our gestureZoomScale.
So this is the simplest possible
thing to do while updating.
We're gonna do a little
more complicated thing
when we do the DragGesture
and panning the thing around.
So that's all that's required
to support this zoom gesture.
We created a zoom gesture,
a MagnificationGesture,
it updates our steady state when it ends.
While it's going on, it
updates this @GestureState,
which is transient, we only do it
while the gesture is happening.
And all we do is attach this
zoom gesture to our ZStack,
so that when that gesture
happens in our ZStack,
we recognize it.
All right, so here's our little document.
Hold down option to get two fingers,
and we can zoom in and zoom out.
And we can still double tap
to show the whole image.
We could also go over here
and get our huge background.
And we can zoom in and out, double tap.
We can do the same thing
for panning around,
'cause if I'm zoomed way in here
and I wanna see this other horse,
I'd like to be able to drag this over.
For pan, I'm not gonna
go through all the detail
of the code again, typing this all in,
because it's very similar
to doing the same thing
we did here with the zoom gesture,
but I am gonna walk
through the code with you.
And for the pan, this is
the code that I just added.
We are going to still
have steadyStatePanOffset,
and still gonna have the gesturePanOffset,
which is gonna be only the
pan while we're dragging,
and then that'll make a pan offset
by adding the two together
and multiplying by zoomScale, of course.
By the way, I am doing some things here
like adding points together,
normally you can't do that in Swift,
but I added some EmojiArt
extensions down here
for point and size, to be
able to make this code here
look a lot simpler.
So you can check those
out if you want as well.
This feels exactly the same, right,
panOffset feels like zoomScale.
It's just taking the steady
state and adding the gesture's
while-in-motion value.
So let's look at panGesture,
looking slightly different
than a MagnificationGesture.
It's a DragGesture.
And on the ended, it's
pretty much the same,
we get our final drag value.
The only thing about this is that
the drag value that's passed to us
is a little more complicated
than it is for a magnification.
For magnification it's
just a simple scale,
that is the value that's passed,
both while we're updating
and when it ends.
But a drag has more information.
So we're gonna go and
actually take a look at this
in the documentation.
Open it up.
Here's DragGesture.
And it's explaining a
little bit this up here.
But down in here you can see,
when we have the .updating and .onEnded,
this value that's being passed to us,
when we're handling things
happening in the gesture,
is actually a type
DragGesture.Value right here.
So I'm gonna click on this .Value
and we're gonna see what it looks like.
You can see that this
value is not a simple Float
like the scale was in
MagnificationGesture.
It's actually a struct
and it has the location
of where you are
currently with the finger,
and also the start location,
where you started from.
Even the time.
So it's time stamped every
single time it updates,
so you can know how fast it's
moving and things like that.
And here's the translation,
which is a CGSize,
width and height, how far
it's gone since the start
of the pan.
And we're gonna use this
translation to update our offset.
So here it is right here,
we're gonna say translation,
just drag value translation in here.
And all we're gonna do
is take the translation,
we have to divide it by
the zoomScale, of course,
and we're gonna add it, in
the end, to our steady state,
and while it's updating,
it's going to be our gesture pan state.
And then we just add those two together.
And off we go.
Otherwise it's very, very similar.
So now that we have this PanOffset,
we just need to use it everywhere
that it makes sense to have a pan.
So that's easy, it's a
lot of the same places
we did the zoomScale.
Right here where we do the
scaleEffect, of course,
we want to offset our View.
Everyone remembers the offset,
you probably used that a lot in homework 3
or maybe through animation,
but here's the offset
for the background image.
How about the offset for the emoji?
So that's here in this position thing.
And, position remember,
is doing the coordinate
system transformation
from (0, 0) in the center and so is drop.
So both of these are going
to need to be adjusted,
both position and this.
Let's do this one first while we're here.
Just gonna throw this right in here,
location equals a CGPoint,
that is the x-location,
but minus the panOffset's width,
and the y is the location.y
minus the panOffset's height.
And then that position right here,
let's go down to fix that.
It's doing the same transition
in the opposite direction actually.
It's right here.
We'll say location equals
a CGPoint which equals x.
x plus the panOffset.width,
and the y is the location.y
plus the panOffset.height.
Plus that, and the only
other thing I wanna do with
panOffset is when I double
click the zoomToFit,
we wanna, I think, reset it to the center.
So let's say steady, our
steadyStatePanOffset equals .zero,
which is the same as
CGSize.zero, by the way.
But, Swift can infer the CGSize for us.
And I think that's all we need to do.
Those are the only places
that the pan matters.
Just moving the background around,
and then making sure
we're doing the right
coordinate system transfer
on the positions of the emojis.
And just like we added the
gesture for a zoomGesture,
let's add the gesture for our panGesture.
And you can add multiple gestures here.
If they might conflict with
each other in some ways,
then there are methods that
you can find in Gesture
for doing Gestures simultaneously,
or even exclusively,
where one Gesture, once it wins,
will not allow the other one.
You can take a look at that
in the Gesture documentation.
All right, let's see.
Woo, there we go.
We can do that, we can
zoom way in, look around,
and zoom out.
So we're now, nice combination
of zooming and panning
throughout our whole document.
Now, you're homework
assignment is going to be
to do the same thing, zooming and panning,
but with these little emoji.
In that case is, moving the emojis around,
and also resizing the emojis
so that they're larger
compared to the background.
And that's really gonna let us
build real beautiful EmojiArt
because we can actually control the sizing
and positioning of things.
So you're gonna have
to manage the selection
of these things, selecting them.
That homework, by the way, is next week.
In your assignment A3, you don't have to,
you're not using any Gestures
in your assignment A3,
this is next week's
homework I'm talking about.
And as I mentioned earlier,
that one data structure
you might wanna use
to keep your selection, is a Set.
So, if you're gonna put your
little Emojis into a Set,
they need to be Hashable.
So let's talk about how that works.
Back here in EmojiArt we
have our Emojis, right here.
And, they're Identifiable,
and they're Codable,
and you can also make them Hashable.
And, if you mark it Hashable,
it means they can be put in a Set.
Note that you don't have to
do anything, it just works.
And that's because, again,
the types in this struct
are such that Swift
can automatically do
this hashability for you.
So not only could you put this in a Set,
but Emojis could also be if
the key is in a Dictionary
if you wanted.
I don't think you're gonna
need that for your homework.
But, I just wanted to
show you that real quick
in case you wanted to do that.
So that's it for today.
We added a lot of cool
features to our EmojiArt.
And we can save it, and
when we leave and come back,
we don't lose all that
wonderful work that we did.
And of course we have double tap,
and we can resize and pan.
So there's a lot more things we can do
to make our EmojiArt even better,
and we'll dive into all of that next week.
- For more, please visit
us at standford.edu.