(peaceful music)
- [Presenter] Stanford University.
- [Paul] All right,
Lecture 7, Stanford CS193p,
Spring of 2020.
Today we're briefly gonna
talk about Colors and Images,
just a couple of minutes.
Then we're gonna dive
into our main topic today
which is multithreaded programming.
And then we're gonna have a humongous demo
and this demo's gonna
cover a lot of ground.
We're gonna somewhat review
MVVM by just developing
a completely separate app from scratch
and that you way you can
compare and contrast that app
with Memorize and it helps
you understand MVVM better.
And then we're gonna talk
about a bunch of miscellaneous topics
and of course we will demo multithreading
since that's our main topic of today.
So Colors and Images, let's
talk about Colors first.
There is a struct called
Color, as you know.
We've been using it so far.
And there's another thing called UIColor.
And you might wonder
why are these two things
that are just named so similarly?
Well a Color, as we learn,
and we talk about this
in the forums actually, can
kind of point different roles.
It can be a Color specifier,
like foregroundColor Color.green
or it can also be a
ShapeStyle, fill Color.blue.
And it could even be a
View, we haven't seen this
in any of our demos so far,
but it can be a View, Color.white.
You can have that appear
anywhere a View appears.
It's quite strange, and so like, kind of,
you get a rectangle filled
with white when you do that.
Now due to Color's multifaceted role
where it can do all
these different things,
it has somewhat limited API.
Mostly just creating Colors
and I think has some stuff
where you can compare Colors
but it's pretty limited.
So there's this other thing, UIColor.
This is the thing where you're actually
going to manipulate colors,
you're going to interrogate the color,
what's your RGB value, and it's
got a lot more system colors
and pre-built-in colors.
It's a much more powerful color class
than this Color thing.
Now it's not a chameleon.
It just is a little container
that represents a color
and it represents it in
a very particular way,
but that's what it is.
And if I'm ever gonna do
any color manipulation,
which you are gonna do, by the
way, in your assignment five.
Not next week but the week after,
you're gonna wanna use UIColor.
But the great thing is once
you've built the UIColor
and transformed it or do
whatever you wanna do to it
to make it the way you
want, now you can just say
Color uiColor: and specify that color
and you can use it in all the ways above,
as a specifier, a View, whatever.
UIColor starts with UI.
That's because it comes from
the old pre-SwiftUI world.
Things that start with UI are from UIKit.
But it was so good at manipulating colors,
yeah, they just brought it
into SwiftUI just like it was.
Now a similar sort of dichotomy happened
with Image and UIImage.
So Image in SwiftUI is primarily a View,
and it's a View that displays an image.
It's not something that you
would make a var of type Image
and it holds an image.
It is a View.
So this Image View you
can specify what image
you want it to display
in a number of ways.
One way is by just giving it a String,
and it will use that
as the name of an image
that it finds in your
Assets.xcassets file.
If you look in Xcode
where all your files are,
there's a file we haven't
talked about in there,
Assets.xcassets, Xcode assets.
And if you look at it you'll
see that it's just a place
to store images in lots
of different formats
and you can get them by name
by saying Image of the name.
That's kind of the most
basic way to access an image.
There are also though
a ton of system images.
And you get this one by
saying Image systemName:
and then the name.
Now how do you find
out what all these are?
Well, you're gonna need to download an app
from developer.apple.com/design
called SF Symbols and it
has all of them listed.
You can search through them by name,
the names pretty much
encapsulate what they are.
When you're there, by the way,
at developer.apple.com/design,
there's a document you'll
see right on that page
called the Human Interface Guidelines.
You really wanna read that document.
I really (chuckles) should have made it
reading assignment number four.
I might go back and still do
that, but you should read it.
It's an absolute must
read if you ever want
to do an App Store submission.
It talks about how your UI is
supposed to do certain things
so that all UIs in all
apps are doing these things
in the same way and the user
gets a consistent experience.
Super important, and, not
just to read that document,
to really understand all of
the things that are in it
so when you go to write your app
and submit it to the App
Store it doesn't get rejected
for violating these Human
Interface Guidelines.
If you use the system
name images, by the way,
you can control how large they are
with the .imageScale View modifier.
It's a little bit hidden there
'cause you don't do it on
somewhere in the image.
So there's actually a View modifier.
So go take a look at that.
And also just a quick
note, the system images
are really good to use as masks.
So like if you have a gradient,
you can have it shine
through the system image
and that can give you
some really cool effects.
So UIImage, that's the
thing that if you had a var
that was gonna hold an image
in it, like a JPEG image,
it would be of type UIImage.
Again, comes from UIKit,
it was so good (chuckles)
at handling images,
there was just no reason
to try and duplicate it
all in the Image View.
And so they just brought it in
and UIImage can do multiple file formats,
JPEGs, GIF, PNGs.
It has transformation
primitives, scaling, all these,
it can do animated images, all that.
And once you've built a
UIImage up to what you want
from whatever JPEG file or
whatever you built it from,
then you can say Image uiImage:,
the UIImage and present it as a View.
So similar kind of,
with Color and UIColor,
Image and UIImage.
All right, main thing of
the day, multithreading.
Now multithreading can
be used to build systems
of parallel computing
where you've got an app
and it's doing multiple
things at the same time.
Maybe they depend on each other,
you want to manage those
dependencies, all these things.
But we're only gonna
talk about multithreading
in this class in one very important niche
that it can satisfy, which
is not blocking the UI.
And we're going to not block the UI
by having all the stuff
that would block the UI
on a different thread of execution.
Now it is never okay for
your UI to be blocked.
If someone reaches with their finger
to scroll something or tap on a button,
your UI has to be ready to do it.
It cannot be saying, "Oh, I'm sorry.
"I'm off doing something else for a second
"or so, I'll be right back."
It has to instantly do it.
But sometimes you need
to do those slow things.
You need to do some huge
machine learning calculation
or something, or you need
to go out over the network
and that's gonna take time.
There's just no avoiding that time.
So how during that time are
you gonna not block your UI?
Well, we're gonna do that
by using different threads of execution.
Now I'm gonna assume most
of you know what a thread is
but I'll just quickly talk about it.
Most modern operating
systems have this ability
to say this code should execute
on its own thread of execution.
And then you can have
multiple threads of execution
all executing simultaneously.
Now they may not actually
be executing simultaneously.
You know, if you have
multiple core processors
or a multi-processor or
something, they might be.
But sometimes you just have a single core
or not enough cores and
so it's actually switching
back and forth between them
really quickly, not doing it.
But you don't care about any of that.
To you, it just appears that
you've got different pieces
of code executing simultaneously.
They're running at the exact
same time somehow, madly.
Now this can be a little
bit complicated to manage
in terms of as a programmer deciding,
well this one wants to be running
on this thread of execution,
this one over here.
So we really need some help in making
this multithreaded code
readable and understandable
by mere mortals like us
and we need this because this time,
this thing about things
running at the same time
adds this fourth dimensions to our code
that's hard for us to grok.
Swift solves this complexity issue
using something called queues.
Now a queue is nothing more
than a bunch of blocks of code
that are sitting in line
just patiently waiting
to get a thread of execution
that will go and run them.
Now and by queue I mean
the same thing as queue
like a queue at the
movies or at least queue
that used to be at the movies
before they closed all the
movie theaters (chuckles)
for coronavirus, but, you know, a line
where people are standing in
line, the same thing here.
These are just blocks of code
waiting in line to get executed.
So with Swift we don't
think about threads.
We don't even think about 'em.
All we think about is queues.
We let the system come
up with all the threads
and all that stuff to take
things off these queues
and execute them, that's up to the system.
All we think about is the
queues and the blocks of code
we want to plop on those queues.
We specify these blocks of
code that go on the queues
using closures, functions as arguments.
We'll see how this works, what
the code looks like for this
but let's just quickly talk about queues
and what queues are available first.
And the most important queue
in all the world of iOS
is called the main queue.
Now this is the queue that has
all the blocks of code on it
that have anything to do with UI.
Anytime you want to do
something in the UI,
you have to use the main queue.
It is absolutely unequivocally an error
to do UI in any block of
code that is not executing,
was not chosen from, the main queue.
So when you tap on a screen,
that is going to execute code
on the main queue.
When you do anything that
draws in the UI in any way,
it's going to get initiated
from the main queue.
There is some stuff like animation
where all the calculations
of the animation,
the inter-frame, the
animatableData that we did in,
that is going to happen in
another queue off the main queue.
But it's all gonna get coordinated
back onto the main queue
to do the drawing, so
the stuff all happens
without smashing into each other.
So where do we do the
long-lived stuff then,
the non-UI stuff, well,
the best place to do it
is in this pile of background queues
that the system makes available to you.
So this is where we're gonna do anything
that's gonna take a long
time like a network call
or some, like I said,
machine learning (chuckles)
or some other analysis
that's gonna take, you know,
more than a millisecond or so to do.
The system has, it
manages a bunch of threads
to go pull blocks of code off
of these background queues
and run them for you.
So things that you put on
these background queues,
they all seem to almost
be running simultaneously
and of course they're
running simultaneously
with what's on the main queue.
But of course, the main queue
always gets higher priority.
If someone taps or if you
put your own block of code
on this main queue, it's
gonna run much more quickly
and with more attention than anything
on these background queues.
The whole system that does all this
is called Grand Central Dispatch
because it's dispatching
the code from the queues
to be executed by the threads.
And it has a number of different functions
in there in Grand Central Dispatch,
but really it boils down to
these two fundamental tasks
that you're doing with GCD.
One is getting a queue
and two, plopping a block
of code on the queue.
And that's pretty much
99% of what GCD is about.
There's more stuff in there coordinating
with when things are
happening on multiple queues,
but for our purposes,
especially for the purposes
of keeping long-lived things
off of the UI main queue,
these are the two main things we need.
So let's talk about the
first of these two things
which is creating or
getting access to a queue.
Now the first one is simple,
that's the main queue.
You're just gonna use this
simple DispatchQueue.main,
right, main is the static function
in the struct DispatchQueue.
And that is the queue you're gonna use
whenever you want to draw in the UI.
Couldn't be simpler, that's all you do.
What about all the background queues?
For that one you're gonna
call this static function
in DispatchQueue called global
which takes an argument qos
which is quality of service
which is kind of like priority.
Essentially how much do we want the system
to pay attention to the
blocks of code on this queue.
And the four options you have
here are userInteractive.
This is for things like
you're in the middle
of dragging something across the screen
and you need to calculate something.
It might take a little bit,
so you can't make the drag
be jaggy but you need
that information now!
So this is a super high
priority (chuckles) queue.
It's gonna get serviced a lot.
Then there's userInitiated.
Here you're not in the middle of a drag,
but the user did just tap on something.
"Do this for me," so you
need to do this right now.
Then there's utility which
is the user didn't just ask
for this, but it needs to be done.
So this is pretty high priority,
but it's not like the user
just clicked a button
and wants this done now.
And then there's background
which is really low priority.
This is, you know, I'm
cleaning up my database
of old cruft or something that's
going on in the background
that really has nothing to do
with what the user perceives
to be their app, but it's something my app
needs to do to have proper
operation or whatever.
And that's it, that's how
you get a queue, super easy.
GCD you're gonna find is amazingly simple
and it's really simple
to get ahold of a queue.
You're either gonna do the main queue
or one of these global background queues.
The second thing is plopping
a closure onto a queue.
Well how are we gonna do that?
Well let's say I have my
queue, either the main queue
or one of these global queues.
And I'm either gonna
call this function async
or the function sync on that queue.
And the argument is just a closure
and it's a function
that takes no arguments
and returns no arguments.
And inside there I'm gonna
put whatever code I want
to be executed on that queue.
Now the second one of
these, the .sync, blocks.
So it blocks and waits 'til that queue,
the green queue right there,
it waits until it has
taken this block of code
off of its queue and
executed it to completion.
Then it's gonna continue.
So we would never call
queue.sync in UI code
because it would block the UI.
In fact, it's rare to
call this .sync at all.
So we're almost always using .async
which means just take this block of code,
throw it on this other
queue, and just keep going.
And so that means that whatever's
in that curly braces there,
it's gonna be executed
some time in the future.
I don't know when, it's
whenever that queue
gets around to it.
Now hopefully if that's the main queue,
it's gonna be pretty soon
but even that's not a
locked, solid guarantee.
So your code has to be
tolerant of the fact
that when you say queue.async blah,
whatever's in the blah
might not be executed for,
you know, many milliseconds,
possibly even longer.
So that's a little bit of thinking
you have to comprehend that
as you write your code.
But async is the one we usually do.
We're just plopping these blocks of code
onto these other queues to
get them to get executed.
Besides async and sync,
there are some other ones.
asyncAfter, which will do the async
but after a little delay
so that you can wait
to have it executed, but mostly
we're gonna be doing async.
Beauty of this GCD API,
when you combine these two things,
having a queue and async
to plop it on there
is when you're nesting these
things inside of each other.
Now let's look at an example here.
So I'm doing DispatchQueue
global userInitiated
so this is something
the user asked me to do
but I'm gonna do it on
a background thread,
not on the main queue.
So I'd call that async
with a block of code
and in that block of code at the beginning
I'm gonna be doing something
that might take a very long time.
Maybe I'm accessing
something on the network
or doing some calculation.
And it's fine to do because
I'm not doing this code,
this curly brace that
has started right there
is not doing something on the main queue.
So that's fine to take as
long as I want right here.
But this longtime thing that we're doing,
when it comes back
maybe it's gonna require
a change to the UI.
Maybe I fetched an image and
now I wanna put that image
on the UI, but we can't do that UI here
because we are currently
on one of these global background queues.
We can't do UI on this queue.
So this code that we
posted async to that queue
can't do UI here.
But that's no problem,
let's just turn around
and post a block of code
that does do the UI thing
back on the main queue.
And the main queue eventually
will get through its queue
and get to this one and execute it.
And again, the main queue, high priority.
It's probably not gonna take long.
It might be nothing on the
queue when you put it on there,
and boom it just runs really quickly.
But conceptually the point is we're taking
this block of code and
telling the main queue,
"Hey, you go run this thing."
And so you can do UI in there.
This makes asynchronous
code almost look synchronous
but they're not quite.
First outer block there, the
outer yellow DispatchQueue
async is, it could take a long time.
And so that inner line
might not be happening
for 10 seconds.
And what if the user is
like totally navigating away
from this in their UI,
they're just not even,
it took so long they
don't even care anymore.
And then you come back and you're like,
"Oh, now I want to put this image up,"
but the user doesn't care
about that image anymore.
They're off doing
something else in the app.
That's why I'm saying you
have to think a little bit
about the time, but at
least it makes it read,
from a conceptual standpoint,
looks almost like
synchronous code right here.
This DispatchQueue.main.async that we saw,
you're gonna often do that.
And the reason you're gonna often do that
when you're doing asynchronous programming
is you're gonna be doing
things in the background
that are gonna result in things
that are gonna affect the UI
and so you're gonna have
to Dispatch main async
back to the UI to do the
UI results of those things.
However you're not actually gonna call
DispatchQueue.global qos very often.
Why aren't you gonna call that very much?
Well, that's because there
are higher-level APIs
for managing this background activities
that you're gonna be calling.
For example, if you
wanted to fetch an image
over the network which we're gonna do
by doing Dispatch global
in the demo later today,
but if you wanted to do it,
you really would use this
thing called URLSession.
So URLSession is a struct
and it takes the information
about the URL you want and it goes off
and it puts something
on the global QoS queues
to go do that.
But you have to be a little careful here
because URLSession also takes an argument
which is a closure you give it
to execute when the image comes back.
That closure is also gonna
be executed by URLSession
on this Dispatch global queue.
So we can't do UI in there.
So whenever you're using
something like URLSession
you give the closure that
says, "Hey, go fetch this
"and when you're done, call this closure,"
that closure is almost
certainly gonna be doing
DispatchQueue.main.async
inside of it to dispatch
and go back to the main
queue to put the UI result
of whatever was fetched by the URLSession.
Now again today, I want
you to understand GCD.
So that's why we're gonna
do the DispatchQueue global
ourselves and then we're gonna do
a DispatchQueue.main.async ourselves.
But in the real world, if
I was fetching an image
which is what we're doing in
our demo, I'd use URLSession.
All right, so let's get
to that demo right away.
I already talked about
what we're gonna be doing,
so let's do it!
This demo is a pretty big one.
We are going to do a whole
nother app from scratch.
That way you can compare and
contrast what you saw us do
in Memorize versus a
completely different app.
And then hopefully all the
things you did in Memorize
won't seem so, you
know, Memorize specific.
You'll see which ones of
them are just general things
that we're doing in every app
versus those specific things.
Let me show you what this
app is going to look like
before we get started here.
It's called EmojiArt and it lets us build
some sort of art here
out of emojis, of course,
'cause we love emojis.
And across the top you can
see we have some emojis
to choose from to build out of
and we can even choose
different kinds of emojis,
activities, animals, whatever.
These lists of emojis
are editable by the user.
If they click on here, they can actually
remove emojis from there
or even click on here
and go to the emoji keyboard
and add more emojis,
maybe add another face
in here or whatever.
And you use the emojis to build your art
but of course it's nice
to have a good background
so I've gone over here to Google.
By the way, this right
here is the iPad multi-app
user interface here where I've
got my EmojiArt on the left
and I've got Safari on the right.
And I can drag Safari
completely away if I want,
just leaving my EmojiArt or go down here
and grab Safari and drag it back out again
and then resize it to
whatever size that I want.
I'm going to choose my background here
by using drag and drop.
Here I have searched for
my favorite thing here,
countryside cartoons, and
I'm just looking around here
for all the countryside
cartoons on the internet.
And I'm just gonna pick
one here and lift it up
and you see when I drag it over,
it gets that little green
plus sign in the corner.
And if I drop, hmm, it
adds it as the background.
We're gonna make it so
you can zoom in here
or we could pan around a little bit.
Then we can add our emojis.
So let's see, let's see if we
can find, here's a bicyclist.
So we'll just pick up
Mr. bicyclist right here,
put him on the road.
And he's a little small,
so I'm gonna select him
and then make him bigger.
Then of course we'd like
some nature as well.
Let's go find some animals.
Oh, a bee, one of my favorite
things in nature is a bee.
Where would we be without bees?
And maybe we'll add
some perspective to this
by having some of the bees
seem to be closer to us
and some of the bees farther away.
So our goal is to build this app.
Now today, all we're going to do
is put this little thing up here.
We're not gonna have a chooser
that lets us choose different kinds,
we're just gonna have
one row of emoji up here.
And we also want to be
able to drag and drop
to do our background, and
we also want to be able
to pick up these emojis
and drop them in there.
Then your homework for
next week is going to be
to be able to select them
and then resize these emojis
or to move them around.
And then next week, we're also going
to add this little chooser
up here and make it
so that these documents persist
'cause right now, if I quit
this app and went back in,
I'd lose my documents.
So we obviously want to
be able to save documents.
And so we got a lot of
work to do with this app,
but let's get started today
with the basics of it.
So this is a completely
brand new project, of course.
Now you don't have to follow along,
you won't be asked to
do that in your homework
like you were the first two weeks.
But again, it's always
recommended as a learning exercise
to follow along.
So let's get started here
by clicking new project.
We always pick Single
View App in this class.
I'm gonna call this thing
EmojiArt, all right.
Everything else the same
as we had for Memorize.
And I'm gonna put it in
Developer right here,
same place as I'm putting my Memorize.
And here it is, let's
go make a lot of space
so that we can see our code very clearly.
We'll even make that a little small there.
Now let's dive right in.
You already know the basics
of how to do things here
so let's start by making our ViewModel.
So I'm just gonna go up
here, File, New, File.
And it's a Swift file,
right, part of the UI
but not a View itself.
Oh, let's make sure we
put it in the right place.
And I'm gonna call my
ViewModel here EmojiArtDocument
because my ViewModel's gonna
represent one document,
one EmojiArtDocument.
And you could imagine some day having a UI
in my EmojiArt that would let
me open different documents
and each one would be represented
with its own ViewModel.
ViewModels of course are UI
so we're gonna important SwiftUI
and they're also classes,
so we're gonna have this
EmojiArtDocument be a class
and we always do ObservableObject
for our ViewModels
because they're the thing
that manage this reactiveness
between things change in the Model
and we see them in the UI.
Now that we have a ViewModel,
let's go back to our View
which is this ContentView right here
with this default ContentView business.
And I'm gonna put my ViewModel here
so I'm gonna have ObservedObject var.
Now I'm not gonna call it viewModel.
That's what we called it before.
I'm gonna call it something
we would actually call it. (chuckles)
In this case document, and
that's an EmojiArtDocument.
We're not gonna do preview
right off the bat here.
Our EmojiArt View is pretty
much all about the things
that are dragged into it,
and of course in the preview
window we can't drag it
in there but eventually
we probably would want
to put that preview back and
have maybe some test data
of some emojis in a background
so that we could see to make
sure that thing looks good.
But for general purposes here,
we'll just turn that off for now.
And I don't like this name
ContentView right here.
That's bad, so let's do the
same thing we did before.
Command click on this and say Rename.
And now it's kind of
searching for all the places,
you can see it here, that this appears.
And so I'm gonna rename this
to be EmojiArtDocumentView.
It's gonna be a View
that shows a document.
And we can see, uh, it's
not going to rename that.
Okay, we'll have to do that ourselves.
It's up here.
And of course, we got to change,
look at the places where this is called
and make sure we create a
ViewModel for these things
and we know that's over
here in our SceneDelegate,
contentView equals EmojiArtDocumentView.
And we'll have the document be for now
just a default EmojiArtDocument,
an empty document.
Doesn't have anything in it.
And it's okay for us to do this initialize
with no arguments 'cause if we
look at our EmojiArtDocument
it has no uninitialized
variables, so it's perfectly fine
to do init that way.
All right, so let's start
building our UI right off the bat
and our UI, if you recall,
has this emoji at the top.
So let's try and build this little nice
scrollable list of emoji
there, see if we can do that.
Now that scrollable list of
emoji, that palette at the top,
that's shared by all documents.
So that does not want to
be a var in an instance
of the document, 'cause
remember an instance
of this ViewModel represents one document.
That wants to be a static var.
And in fact, for now we're
gonna make him static let,
this palette of emoji,
and well, we'll just put some
random things in here for now.
We know how to add emojis.
We'll go here, sure, put a star in there,
some clouds, what else we got down here?
An apple, yeah, maybe a earth.
And then what else we got, a pretzel,
yeah, and I don't wanna make you hungry
so I won't put any food in there.
But maybe like a baseball,
that kinda thing.
All right, so this is just
gonna be our default palette.
Eventually this is going to
become an Array of palettes
so that we can have that
nice chooser right here
where we can choose
between these palettes.
But for now, we're not, we
don't have that feature.
And so now that we have this palette,
let's just make our document View
instead of saying "Hello, World!"
let's have it display that.
Now this should be something you can
kind of instantly imagine
how we're gonna do.
We're just gonna make
an HStack of ForEach.
And the ForEach is going to
be those EmojiArtDocument,
that static palette.
And then for each of the emojis in there
we want to just put a Text of the emoji.
Now this doesn't quite work
because this is a String
and ForEach remember wants an Array,
either a range of Ints
or it wants an Array
of Identifiable things.
And so a String is not an Array.
It's close, but there's a
great little function on String
called map which will
turn it into an Array
by calling a function,
which we're going to
call String zero here.
And this function takes each
character in the String,
so $0 is a character in the String
and it just, we're gonna
apply this function to it.
But we're just gonna
turn it into a String.
So String knows how to
take a single character
and turn it into a String.
And so now we have ForEach
on an Array of Strings.
This map returns an Array of Strings.
So that's cool, and
that means this emoji's
gonna be a String.
But it's still not working.
We're getting the dreaded
Oh, expected range of Int.
And we know why that is.
ForEach takes an Array of Identifiable
and Strings are not Identifiable.
Now it's interesting, we could
put an extension on String
to make it Identifiable, like this.
Just by doing var id.
And I have a cool way to do that.
I'm gonna have the id be a String.
I'm just gonna return
myself, okay I'm a String.
Strings are equatable.
By the way, this don't care
for the id and Identifiable,
it's not a complete don't care.
Obviously this id has to be Equatable.
You have to be able to say == on it.
Otherwise I can't tell if
two Identifiable things
are the same.
But a String, you can certainly do == on
so this is fine.
But what's this error that I'm getting.
"Property id must be declared public
"because it matches a requirement
"in a public protocol 'Identifiable.'"
Well, Identifiable is
indeed a public protocol
and String is a public class.
So that makes us have to
mark this also as public.
Now what does public mean?
We have not seen the
access control public.
We saw private, and private
set, but we haven't seen public.
Public means non-private in a library.
Identifiable and String
are clearly in the SwiftUI
imported library right here.
And so they have to mark
things that they want people
outside the library to actually
be able to see with public.
Now you'd not gonna be doing
libraries in this class
so you're never gonna
mark anything public.
But if one day you do work on a library,
you'll know what public
is all about there.
Now this does work, you
see, no errors, right?
This is now an Array of Identifiables
because Strings are Identifiables.
But this is also wrong, okay.
We really wouldn't (chuckles)
want to make Strings Identifiable
throughout our entire app.
That's really, we only want them
to be Identifiable right here.
And ForEach understands
that you're sometimes
gonna pass an Array of
something that you don't,
you can't make it conform to Identifiable.
So it has a nice little extra argument
you could specify called id.
Now id lets you specify
which var on these things
to use to uniquely identify it.
So it's essentially like
use this var as the id
as if this thing were Identifiable,
which is really really convenient.
Now the var that I'm gonna
use in String is .self.
Okay, (chuckles) so every
object essentially has a var
you can't see called
self and that is itself.
So that's a great identifier for a String.
But what is this syntax
right here, \.self?
This is called a key path in Swift.
And a key path is just a
really cool simple syntax
to be able to specify a
var on another object.
So here, this is backslash
means this is a key path
and dot means on this thing right here,
this class of things, String, self.
And I could press any, you know, any var.
I could even say like this, foo.bar
and call a var to return
something, then call a var on that.
It's a pretty flexible little system,
this little key path oriented stuff.
But you can see that fixes
everything right here.
So let's run it and see what we got here.
And let's not run on an iPhone.
So this app that we're doing right here
is going to be an iPad app.
I'm gonna make it primarily for the iPad.
We're gonna find that because
of the power of SwiftUI,
it's going to work (chuckles)
quite well on the iPhone
as well but we're gonna
develop it on the iPad first.
We drag and drop and all these
things we want over here.
So there it is, yeah
this shows Safari here
and now we're running our
version of EmojiArt over here
so we lost all the stuff that
I was showing you before.
But here they are, look
at that, those are emojis.
Now, well our emojis have a little bit
of some problems here.
One, they're really small and we want 'em
to be scrollable, so let's
go fix some of these things.
The smallness, we know how to fix that.
We're just gonna say .font
and we'll use a system font
of size and I'm gonna be
a good programmer here
and actually make a little let down here,
probably a private let
called my defaultEmojiSize.
It's gonna be CGFloat.
I'm gonna say 40, I think I tried that out
and it seemed pretty good.
So let's say
self.defaultEmojiSize right here.
That'll make it big.
Let's see what that looks like.
Yeah, okay, definitely much better.
That's closer to what
we were having before.
What about the scrollability?
I'm dragging on this, it's not scrolling
back and forth here,
that's super easy in Swift.
So this is so easy, I was
thinking of having slides
on this (chuckles) and
how to do ScrollViews
but it's so easy, it's
really hardly even worth
having a slide over.
You just put it in a
ScrollView and a ScrollView
will let you specify whether
it scrolls horizontally
or vertically or both.
So our ScrollView obviously
only scrolls horizontally.
We just wrap this in there
and that's all we have to do.
Now this HStack that we had
is going to be scrollable.
You see, I can scroll it around.
And one thing I don't
like, it's kinda close
to the edge right there.
I want a little bit of
room and we know how to do,
add a little bit of room to things.
So let's take this ScrollView
and add a little padding.
And I'm only gonna do
padding horizontally.
You've probably gathered by now
how the padding has a lot
of different arguments.
You can specify exact
paddings on just some edges
or default paddings or whatever.
This is gonna give me the default padding
but only on the left and right.
And I probably want the,
vertically I want this thing
to use as little space as possible.
So I don't really want padding there
'cause I want my document
to be as big as possible.
Speaking of my document,
let's get my document on there
and have this push up to the top
and my document use all the
rest of the space over there.
It's until we write the code
that actually does a document
that can have a background
and have all those emojis
on there, I'm just going
to use a yellow rectangle
to be my document.
So I'm gonna put it in a VStack
here with this ScrollView
that we just built for the emoji,
and a rectangle that is
foregroundColor yellow.
And well, that's pretty
darn close (chuckles)
to already looking exactly what I want.
Okay, I've got my scrollable
list of emoji up here.
We could have any amount
of emoji we wanted.
And here's my document.
The only thing is I really
don't want this white line
down here, why is this not
yellow all the way to the bottom?
And it's not yellow all
the way to the bottom
because it's only drawing
this yellow in the safe area,
what's called the safe area of this View.
And it considers this little
area down here not safe
because it's got this little,
you see this little bar right here?
That's the bar that you
use if you want to switch
to other apps in the iPad.
And so it considers that an adornment
that's always on the screen.
By default, it doesn't draw over that
in case there's something critical
that your app is drawing behind it.
But our app, we're gonna be
able to zoom and pan around
so if there was some
critical emoji (chuckles)
underneath this bar, we just move it,
move our document out
of the way a little bit.
So we do want to move to
the edges right there.
And in general in iOS
when we are building apps,
content is king.
We want to use as much space
as possible for our content
and as little space as
possible for adornments, okay,
these little things like that
or like, or even our emoji here.
We want to try and keep that kinda small
so we have this huge
space for our document.
So how do we tell
SwiftUI, "Yeah, go ahead,
"use these unsafe areas like
this little thing right here."
By the way, the notch on the
iPhone is also an unsafe area.
So if want to use that,
that is no problem.
We're just gonna go to our rectangle here
and say edges ignoring the safe area
are, and I'm gonna do the
horizontal edges left and right
and also the bottom edge.
So I can do multiple areas to ignore here.
So let's see what that looks like.
Whoo-hoo!
We want to make that yellow
rectangle be our document
so we need a Model for that document.
Now our Model for that
document is just going to be
the background and then all the emoji
and where they are and what size they are.
That is, that's the entire Model.
Now don't get confused here
and maybe just because you did
Memorize and you had themes,
you might be a little
wondering what's going on here.
Yes, the Model for an EmojiArtDocument
is representing a visual
thing, the emoji art itself.
But it's not itself a UI element.
It's still a kind of device
independent representation
of an EmojiArtDocument, it's up to some UI
like SwiftUI to turn it into
something that we can draw.
And I'm gonna emphasize this
by making the coordinates
of these emojis and the size be Ints,
and clearly SwiftUI doesn't work in Ints,
it works in CGFloat, right,
floating point numbers.
But I'm gonna make 'em Ints
just so you can be really
seeing the difference between my Model,
which is this device
independent, UI independent
representation of it and my UI.
So let's go create that Model.
We're gonna go File, New up here.
And it is a Model, so it's a Swift file.
It's all in the right places.
I'm gonna call my Model EmojiArt.
That is what my Model is, it's emoji art.
Here it is, I'm not gonna
change to SwiftUI here.
Just going to import Foundation.
It's a simple struct called EmojiArt
and it has this backgroundURL.
I'm gonna store the URL for background.
It's gonna be of type
URL, optional URL though.
This URL is just a Swift library struct
that holds a URL like https://.
That is a URL and it holds it
and it also can hold file URLs in there.
And the reason I'm making this optional
is that our documents obviously start out
with no background and it's actually valid
to have an EmojiArtDocument
with no background.
It would just be probably
white or something.
It wouldn't look that good maybe.
But it's certainly legal, so that's why
I'm gonna make this an optional.
The other thing is the emojis.
So the emojis are just gonna
be some Array of emojis
of some sort, so I'm gonna
have to have a struct Emoji
that represents the emojis.
Just like we had card in Memorize,
here we happen to have
emojis in our EmojiArt.
And what is in an Emoji?
It's obviously the text,
right, the actual emoji
like the smiley face or whatever.
It's got position and I told you
I'm gonna do position using Ints.
Take note here, by the way,
that I'm gonna have the
coordinate system of this X and Y
have (0, 0) right in the
center of my document.
And that's different from
iOS's coordinate system.
You'll remember from when we did our Pie
that that coordinate system
is (0, 0) in the upper left.
And I'm gonna have X and
Y here be in the center.
And note that because
later on when we're working
in our View, we're gonna have to convert
from this coordinate system of our Model
which is, it's (0, 0) is the center,
to our iOS coordinate
system (0, 0) upper left.
So also we go to size, we can
do that with an Int as well.
Notice that I made the text be a let.
Once you create an emoji in
EmojiArt like a smiley face
or a panda or a bicycle
or whatever (chuckles)
it is going to always be that.
We're never gonna allow
you to change that emoji.
And that's just the decision I made
and I make that decision
or I express that decision
by having this be a let.
Now we can already
anticipate that in our UI
this emoji is gonna
want to be Identifiable.
And clearly we're gonna have to ForEach
through our Emojis and
show them all on screen.
So I'm gonna make this Identifiable.
And that requires us to do this var id.
Now what is our id gonna be?
In our Memorize game, we
made it be like pretty much
which pair does like, first
pair it with zero and one,
the second pair it was two and three.
And here we don't really
have that kind of pairs
or anything like that to use.
There is something that we'll
often use for ids called UUID.
This is a very unique identifier.
In the universe it's unique.
It's a little bit of overkill
for the Emojis in EmojiArt.
I could have hundreds
of Emojis in EmojiArt
and I could have hundreds
of EmojiArt documents.
So this is a lot of these,
generating these unique IDs
kind of for nothing.
And really this id also only
needs to be Identifiable
and unique within this document.
We are not going to need to identifiably
see Emoji across many documents.
So I'm going to actually
have this be an Int
which I'm gonna manage in this struct.
And so it's gonna be privately managed.
Only EmojiArt is going
to know what makes this
Int how we make this Int.
But of course Identifiable
is a public thing,
so people would look at the Int.
And since we only want anyone
to ever look at this file,
you can certainly make it a let.
But what we need to do now is
every time this is created,
I give it a unique ID.
And that is going to be done
with a little private var
called uniqueEmojiId.
It's just gonna be an Int
and I'm gonna add a function
called addEmoji.
And all addEmoji is
gonna do is add an Emoji
by appending a new Emoji
which I'm gonna create
with a standard constructor there.
And unique ID as the id.
Now of course I need to keep
this unique ID being unique
so each time someone does this,
I'm gonna say uniqueEmojiID += 1.
That way it's changing all the
time and always being unique.
Now this is great, but you
can see I've got errors here
all over the place.
"Left side of mutating
operator isn't mutable.
"Self is immutable, self
is immutable." (chuckles)
And yes, this is a function
that mutates self, right?
It changes this guy.
So we need to mark this
as a mutating func.
Now this strategy of
doing this uniqueEmojiID
will work great as long as
everyone always adds Emojis
by calling addEmoji.
But what if someone creates
an Emoji with their own id
and then adds it right here to this Array?
That could be bad, especially
if they choose an id
that's the same as some other one we chose
with that Emoji.
Now you might think private set, right,
private set ought to fix this problem
because that makes it so that emojis
can only be written by us.
But I actually don't want that
because some of these Emoji
things like the position
and the size I do want
people to set those.
And they can set them all they want,
move the emojis around
as much as they want.
So I really can't use private set here
like I did in Memorize.
So how am I going to
protect this from happening
where people are adding
Emoji, not calling this.
I'm gonna do that in an interesting way.
In Emoji here, I'm going to define an init
and it's gonna have all the same arguments
as the standard init that you
get for free for a struct.
Now how does this help the problem?
In fact, it seems like a big waste.
I get this for free, why
would I do this at all?
And the reason I'm gonna do it
is because I'm gonna
make this init private.
By making this init private,
now nobody can create an Emoji
except for Emoji itself,
it's kinda not useful here.
Even EmojiArt though can't create it.
So it does protect against
someone else creating an Emoji
and putting it in here but
it's protecting EmojiArt
from doing it too.
I'm gonna show you a way around that
with a different kind of access
control called fileprivate.
fileprivate makes this
private in this file.
And that gives EmojiArt
the power to call this
and create this but no one
outside this file can do it.
So now we've protected against that case
where someone creates an
Emoji and puts it in here
without going through
our nice unique EmojiID
since there's no way for
them to create an Emoji.
All right, so that's it
basically for our Model.
Our Model is very simple.
Let's go over to our ViewModel over here
and add this as a @Published private var.
And again, I could call it
Model but I'm not going to.
I'm gonna call this my
emojiArt, it's of type EmojiArt.
And let's just set it to a empty EmojiArt
with no background and
no emoji to start with.
And it's published because
every time the EmojiArt changes
of course we need to use our
ObservableObject mechanism
to cause our View to redraw.
And it's private because
I'm going to be a very good
little ViewModel here
and do one of my jobs
which is to interpret
the Model for the View.
So I'm a UI guy, I'm a UI
person, this ViewModel.
I know that we use CGFloats and CGPoints
and CGSizes, we don't use Ints.
And I know that's what
my View's gonna expect.
So I'm going to provide some Intents.
Mark Intents here.
And these Intents, we're gonna type 'em in
real fast there (chuckles) with a snippet.
These Intents are going to
essentially take arguments
to addEmoji like at location CGPoint
and size CGFloat,
or moveEmoji by offset CGSize,
or scaleEmoji by a scale CGFloat.
And then it's just going to turn around
and access its Array, but Intifying them.
See, Int, Int, we're doing Int.
We're making these things into Ints.
So this makes it so my
View is gonna call these.
It can't access emojiArt
directly, it's private.
So it's gonna call these Intent functions,
intend, I intend to add an Emoji,
I intend to move Emoji around, et cetera.
Now notice we have an error here.
"Cannot convert value type
EmojiArt," blah blah blah.
It's because I'm using
firstIndex matching.
Remember that cool function that we added
via an extension to Array
that would look up something
that's Identifiable in
an Array of Identifiables
and find the index of it?
And I'm doing this inside my ViewModel
'cause I also don't want
my View to necessarily
have to deal with indexes into the Array.
Now in Memorize, we used
index into the Array
and why did we use index into the Array?
Because we wanted to
make changes to the Array
right in place and we want
to do the same thing here.
So I'm gonna use index as Array here.
But I'd really like for
my View to just be able
to use EmojiArt objects.
And since they're
Identifiable, when they ask me
to move one or to scale one,
I'll just use this firstIndex matching
to look it up by the same
Identifiable that's here
that's in my emojiArt Emojis list,
all right, since these are Identifiable.
And just a little different
API here than having to View,
have to say moveEmoji at index by offset.
Now of course firstIndex
matching was something we added
in Memorize, so it's not here,
that's why it's complaining.
Now I actually put it in here, this file,
which I'm gonna drag in
and which I provided to you
and I'm definitely gonna
copy this in, not link it in.
And this extension not only
has this firstIndex matching,
it has some other stuff
you're gonna see later on,
things that are just kinda of utilities
and make the code, this
demo go a little quicker.
And here's firstIndex but
it's kind of interesting,
I didn't add it to Array.
Here we did Array in our Memorize,
but here I'm doing collection,
now what is collection?
Collection is a protocol
that Array implements.
And since Array implements that protocol,
if I add an extension
to it, Array gets this.
And so this will work with any collection.
Now why did I add it to
collection here instead of Array?
Well because Set also
implements a collection.
So if I have a Set, you
know, the SwiftUI Set
not the set your homework
three. (chuckles)
SwiftUI Set, if I have one of those
I can do firstIndex
matching on it as well.
And I'm even gonna put this
contains matching element also
so that I can go look and see
inside of a Set or an Array,
do you contain this thing by matching it?
So I'm doing the same
$0 equals element.id.
Why do I do that, by the way?
Well I think when you
do your assignment four
and you're having to manage
the selection of all those Emojis,
pretty good chance you might
want to put them in a Set.
You probably could put 'em into an Array,
but Sets are nicer than Arrays
because they manage identity
and you never want the same Emoji
inside of your selection twice.
And it's real easy to take 'em
in and put 'em out in a set.
So if you want to do that,
you don't have to use this.
So any of this stuff,
okay, this is just provided
for your use if you want to,
but you might want to use Sets.
So that's why I'm putting that here.
All right, back to our ViewModel.
Now if we compile on
this side, it'll succeed
and we have built our
Intents here for the emojis.
But there's one more Intent I might have
which is to set the background URL,
which I'm gonna do with drag and drop.
So I need one more here which
is func setBackgroundURL
and it's just going to
take a URL here, URL,
type URL, again optional, we allow that.
And we'll just have our
emojiArt.backgroundURL
equal this URL.
I'm gonna do one other
little thing right here
which is that these URLS
that you drag and drop
from the internet, sometimes
they're kinda funky URLs
that have the actual URL
(chuckles) for the image
embedded inside of them using this thing
called image URL right here, I-M-G-U-R-L.
So I put a little thing on
URL to extract that image URL
if it's in there out of
these more complicated URLs.
So I'm gonna call this little
imageURL var right here.
Okay, and if, by the way,
if imageURL goes and looks
and it can't find that
funky little embedded thing
then it just returns the URL itself.
So if you drag a normal URL
in, that'll work as well.
So now our ViewModel is fully prepared
to support the View in doing
what the View wants to do.
And so let's go over to
our View and implement it.
Now the first thing I want to implement
is that drag and drop all right.
So over here in our simulator,
if we have our EmojiArt
with Safari on here
and I pick this up, I want to be able
to drop it in here but notice
it's really not working.
It, I don't know, when
we did it the first time
you noticed there was a little green plus.
I'm not getting the green
plus and when I let go,
it doesn't, it fails
to drop and goes back.
So I want it to drop and
I want it to draw here.
I'm also not gonna be yellow anymore.
I'm gonna use a white background.
I think that looks better
when we don't have an image
or if our image is small, having white's
gonna look better than yellow.
So let's do this drag and drop.
Now before we go do drag and
drop, a couple of things.
First of all, this only works in iOS 13.4.
So if you're not on the latest Xcode,
this part of this demo, it's
just not going to work for you.
The second thing is drag and drop,
it's a little bit of sophisticated API.
It's very simple in SwiftUI,
but it uses some old technology
from the Objective-C world.
And so don't be too caught
up in the details of this.
I want you to conceptually
understand what's going on.
I'm not gonna ask you to do
drag and drop in your homework
but it might be something you want to do
in your final project so this
would be a good opportunity
to understand it from that point of view.
So drag and drop works very simply.
You just call this method
on anywhere you want
to be able drop, you just say onDrop.
And onDrop takes some argument
here which I'm gonna type
in and then we'll go over what they are.
This first argument of, this
is saying what kind of thing
do you want to drop and we
want to drop public image.
So public image is a, what's called a URI.
It specifies kind of a public agreement
of the type of things that are images.
Now we're looking for a URL, not an image.
But if you drag and drop an
image, very likely the provider
of that image can also
provide you its URL.
So that is what we are
going to have dropped.
If I said in here that
we wanted URLs dropped,
we might get URLs from non-images
that would be useless to us.
So that why the kind
of thing we're looking
to be dropping here is images.
Now I'm not gonna talk about URIs.
You can look up URIs in the documentation
and understand what they are.
We're actually gonna
put another one in here
in a few minutes, but it's
pretty straightforward
what a URI is.
Now this isTargeted.
That is a good thing we don't need this
because the argument to this
is what's called a Binding.
We're gonna talk all
about Bindings next week.
But we haven't talked about 'em yet
so if I had to explain it
now, that would be bad.
But all this is doing is
basically letting us know
when someone's dragging over us.
Not when they drop, but
when they're dragging over.
Luckily I don't care, I just care
when you drop that thing on me.
And then the third argument
to onDrop is a function,
a closure, that has two arguments.
One is providers.
These are objects called NSItemProviders
that provide the information
that's being dropped.
Now this information being
dropped might be big,
like it might actually be an image.
We're only gonna grab the URL,
but you could grab the
whole image and that's big.
And so that transfer has
to happen asynchronously
and we're gonna talk all
about asynchrony in this demo.
That's one of the primary
things we're doing in this demo.
But we're not, we're gonna
gloss over the asynchrony here
in these providers.
I put again some code over
here in this EmojiArtExtensions
to handle that stuff for us.
And so don't worry about
the asynchrony of this.
We'll be talking all about
asynchrony in just a moment here.
And then the second
argument to this function
is the location of the drop.
Now for the background, we
don't care where it was dropped.
You drop it anywhere in
our big yellow, currently,
rectangle, we're gonna accept the drop.
So we're not gonna do anything
with location for now.
But eventually we're gonna
be dropping emoji on there
and then we will care about
location, but not yet.
So what do we have to do in here?
This function that we're given is supposed
to return whether the drop succeeded.
So I'm gonna create another
little function for that
called drop with the providers,
pass those providers over.
And it's gonna return
whether the drop succeeded.
So, just gonna do that.
A little private func
here, drop providers.
And these providers are an Array
of, as I said, NSItemProvider.
This thing, I'm not gonna
get into what this is.
It's kind of an old
Objective-C thing right there.
And this returns a Bool with it,
which is whether the drop succeeded.
All we need to do here because
of that little extension
I provided is go try and load
a URL from these providers,
see if these providers can
provide me an actual URL.
I'm asking for images, so
they might not be able to
but usually they do.
So I'm gonna let a little
variable found equal providers
that's the Array of those item providers,
load up the first object
of type URL.
And when you specify type as an argument,
you say URL.self, that
means the actual type URL.
This just a static var in the type URL
that returns the type itself.
And that works for instances,
it also works for classes.
So I'm able to do that.
Then it calls a little
function where it passes you
the URL that it was able to find.
And this is just the URL that it was able
to load the first one of.
And all we need to do now
is just ask our document,
our ViewModel, to please
set the background URL
to this thing that was just dropped on me.
To make sure this is working,
I'm gonna actually print
out here dropped URL
and print out what was dropped on this.
So it would make sure
that this dropping stuff
is actually working
before go and figure out
how to get this URL to show up.
So I'm gonna return this found
whether or not the drop worked,
that's what loadFirstObject
return is whether it worked.
That's it for drag and drop. (chuckles)
This is really simple
actually to do drag and drop.
The complication comes a
little bit inside here.
I encourage you if you want
to understand drag and drop
to go and see if you can
figure out that code.
So let's run and see if we're at least
getting this print to happen.
There we go, so I'm gonna
pick up our image, drag.
I can already see something's different.
The green plus that's
appearing in the corner
of the image, that's good, and drop.
And it didn't do anything, of course,
'cause we don't do anything with the URL.
But it did do it here, down
here, saying dropped this URL
and in fact this is one of those URLs
that has this weird imgurl
thing embedded in it.
See, this is the actual URL there.
So it's good thing we dragged, you know,
dragged this thing out of
here or this would not work.
But this is great.
So we have this URL, we
set it as our document's
background URL in our
ViewModel, setBackgroundURL,
which sets it in our Model over here.
And all is well.
The only thing that's left to do now
is actually show that image. (chuckles)
All right, we've got
the URL of that image,
but nowhere in our View right here
do we actually show the image.
All we show now is a rectangle,
edges ignoring that takes a drop.
So how are we going to do that?
We need to do that
essentially by replacing
this Rectangle
foregroundColor yellow here.
I'm gonna replace it by making
it be a white Rectangle.
And overlaid on top of it
is going to be an Image
that has our document's backgroundImage.
Now this line of code's
got a lot to unpack here.
So let's unpack this piece
by piece what's going on here
'cause it's not actually gonna work as-is.
The first thing is I
took a white Rectangle
and I overlaid my Image on top of it.
Why did I do that, why didn't I just
make a ZStack here, right?
ZStack overlays one
View on top of another.
And this has to do with sizing
because we want our
document View, or whatever,
to be sized like it was a Rectangle.
Basically we wanted to use
all the space offered to it.
We know that Shapes take all
the space offered to them
so that's what we want.
We wouldn't want it to
size it to the Image
because Images, these Views, Image,
they size themselves to
the size of the image.
So if you had a small image,
we would have a small little View there
and we want it to be as big as possible.
There is also something called background
which does the same kind of thing.
Sizes to this and then puts
whatever View is in here
as a background for the other image.
So this is all about sizing.
Using overlay or using
background, all right, right here,
is all about the sizing
behavior that you want.
All right, otherwise this is very much
like a two-View ZStack essentially.
So it's still not quite right here.
We're still making our way through this.
This Image right here,
it takes some argument
which is supposed to be
this image, backgroundImage,
but what is backgroundImage?
We don't have a backgroundImage
in our document.
So let's add that.
Let's go over here, I'm
just gonna add a var
backgroundImage and what
type is this gonna be?
You'd think this might be a type Image
but it's not really a type Image.
We're creating the Image View right here.
So this type Image, this
is a struct, it's a View.
Really what we want to pass
to it is an actual image.
And an actual image in
SwiftUI is represented
by another thing called a UIImage.
Now UIImage, things that start with UI
come from the old world, the
previous-to-SwiftUI world.
And this was such a great little object
for dealing with images that
they decided just to keep it.
And they did the same thing with UIColor.
And we saw that before that we have Color.
Color is kind of like a
View, but UIColor is a thing
that actually represents Colors.
By the way, I talked about
UIColor being a View.
UIColor also can be a
specifier right here,
foregroundColor Color.white.
This is not a View, we're just
specifying the Color white.
But Color can act like a View.
I could even say Color.white right here,
and that's perfectly legal. (chuckles)
This can be a View and we also know
that Color can be ShapeStyle,
fill Color or stroke Color in a Shape.
So Color's kind of a chameleon,
can be a lot of different things.
But Image here is the View.
We can say uiImage as
the constructor for it
and pass it a UIImage and
that will make the Image.
And we're often doing this
when we create an Image.
We're gonna learn other
ways to create Images,
but one way is we just pass it a UIImage.
Now this isn't quite working either
and that's because this
does not really want
to be a UIImage, it's an optional UIImage.
Because again, we might
not have the background.
Even if we have the URL,
we might not have gone
and got the image yet.
So this has to be able to be nil.
Another important thing here
is I want this to be private set.
Only our ViewModel is
going to be fetching images
from the internet.
Our View is just going to
look at whatever image arrives
from the internet.
All right, so our View gets the drop,
it sets the backgroundURL,
and then it's our ViewModel
that's gonna have to go off
and create this background image.
So that creates a problem though,
making this be an optional
because this Image uiImage constructor
will not take an optional.
This has to be non-optional.
So it kinda makes me want to go in here,
and say, "Yeah, I'll just have to say
"if self.document.backgroundImage
"does not equal nil, then I'll
create this image right here
"and I'll force unwrap it."
And this looks like, oh, this should work
except for the problem is that
the arguments that overlay
somewhat unusually is not a ViewBuilder.
This didn't have curly braces,
there was no curly brace there.
This is an actual View,
this has to be a View.
And we can't do ifs here.
This is supposed to be a View.
This is an if statement, not a View.
So if we want to do this nice
ViewBuilder if stuff here,
we need to wrap this in
something that does ViewBuilder
and that's what Group is really good at.
So if you find yourself having
to pass a View somewhere,
but you need to do the
if business around it,
go ahead and use a Group because a Group
does not otherwise modify
the layout or anything
of that View, so it's a nice
little trick to use Group.
All right, excellent.
So everything's fine, no errors,
(chuckles) everything compiled.
The only problem is this is
just always going to be nil.
We never set this to anything.
Our ViewModel is to take this URL
and go fetch it on the internet.
And when it gets the actual
image and makes a UIImage
out of whatever it finds
over there on the internet,
then it should automatically
draw in our View.
As long as we make this
backgroundImage also Published.
We need to publish this so
that whenever this changes,
our View causes to redraw and
this whole thing will happen,
this overlay will change, and
we'll get to see that image.
Especially when you're
doing your ViewModel,
it can be easy to remember,
"Oh, yeah, of course,
"my Model is published."
But there might be other
things that your ViewModel
is doing that you want
your View to react to.
And we just do that with @Published.
Now really some ways, the meat
of today's lecture (chuckles)
is how are we gonna fetch
this backgroundImage
and create a UIImage
from this URL down here?
We're gonna do that in
its own little function.
I'm gonna call this function
fetchBackgroundImageData.
And it's gonna go fetch
the background image data
and make a UIImage out of it.
So let's create that little func,
it's a little private func here.
This function's only
job is to set this var.
Once it sets this var to
some UIImage that it gets
from this URL, everything's
just gonna update, right.
We have reactive UI,
we've already built our UI
to deal with this image.
So it should all just happen
automatically once we set this.
So our goal here in the
side here (chuckles)
is to do one thing and one
thing only, set this var.
All right, so what are
we gonna do to do that?
Well first thing is if
you're asking me to go fetch
the background image data,
I'm gonna set my current
backgroundImage to nil.
So I'm in the process of
going out in the internet
and getting something.
That might take quite awhile.
Maybe it's a big image or
maybe the server that it's on
is really slow.
So in the meantime, I'm gonna
clear the backgroundImage
just to let you know,
yeah I know you changed
the backgroundImage, you
dropped something on me.
And I'm working on it.
Really what we'd like
to do is provide some UI
to give some feedback
that we're working on it.
Maybe we will actually
demo that, time permitting.
But we definitely need
to give some feedback
that, "Yeah, we saw that drop
and we're working on it."
So that's that, and then
if the URL that was dropped
which is this emojiArt.backgroundURL now,
if that's nil then there's
no need to go fetch anything.
So I'm gonna put this if let url around it
so that I'm only doing any fetching
on the internet (chuckles)
if I've actually
got a URL to go look for.
So fetching the information
from a URL is really simple.
There is a more sophisticated
mechanism for doing this.
We're gonna do the simplest one
'cause we were only really focused
on the asynchronous programming
that's going on here.
But if you were really
gonna be downloading stuff
from the internet, you
would use URLSession.
And I'm not gonna talk about
the whole URLSession API
but essentially it's
just a closure-based API.
You pass closures to it, it
goes and downloads stuff.
It calls your closures when
the downloads come back
or it'll call other
closures when errors occur.
But a simple way to
fetch data is just to say
if let imageData equal,
try getting the data
from the contents of that URL.
This Data is just an object, a struct,
and it has initializer
where you give it a URL
and it will go out on the internet
and get the data at
that URL and return it.
This can encounter all kinds of errors:
internet timeouts, all
kinds of things happening.
So that's why we have to do this try.
And in next week's reading assignment,
you're gonna learn about
try and thrown errors.
I'm not gonna talk about it today,
but just know that there
are some constructors
that you call and some
functions that you call
that have to be try-ed.
And when you do this try
with a question mark,
it means try this and
if it fails, (chuckles)
network timeout,
whatever, just return nil.
And since I'm doing if let,
this in here won't get
executed if this fails.
Now a huge problem with this line of code.
This could take 10 seconds or two minutes
depending on what the timeout is.
Certainly probably gonna
take at least a half a second
or a second, and during
that time my whole app
is stuck waiting for this line
of code (chuckles) to execute
and that is the rub.
That we can never allow to happen.
We can never call a function
like this that blocks our code
waiting for it to return
because it can take seconds to do this.
Never call that in the
same thread of execution
as all of our UIs
happening, otherwise our app
is going to freeze and the
user's gonna be clicking
and typing and trying
to drag a new thing in,
and, "I, I didn't want that
URL, it's taking too long."
No, they can't do anything.
Our app, they can't even
scroll their emoji at the top.
It's all frozen because our
app is sitting right here
on this line of code for 10
seconds, 15 seconds, whatever.
So how do we get around that?
We use what we talked about in the slides,
the dispatch mechanism.
So I'm going to dispatch
this code to a global queue.
And the quality of service I want here
is called userInitiated.
Remember there's these
different qualities of service.
I want userInitiated because
that's exactly what happened.
The user initiated a request here.
And so that right there,
that that you've seen,
this DispatchQueue.global,
that gives me a global queue,
a queue that executes its
code off the main queue,
not where the UI is.
And I'm going to asynchronously ask it
to perform this function.
This function takes no
argument, return no arguments.
And I'm just gonna ask it
please perform this function
off on this queue, whatever it is,
and I'll have nothing else
to do with you, just do it.
So I'm gonna put this inside here now.
And this is great because
now this is blocking still,
still taking five seconds, but
off on some background queue,
not in the same queue where all the code
for our UI is being executed.
So that's great.
Now the imageData comes back, let's say.
You know, let's say there was no error
and so this try, that
it didn't return nil.
And now I've got the imageData!
It's JPEG data or PNG data
or some kind of data from the internet.
And I need to turn it into a UIImage
'cause that's what I'm trying to do here
is make this UIImage here.
And luckily UIImage has
a great way to do that.
I could just say
backgroundImage equals UIImage
with this Data.
This line of code has a
humongous problem, okay.
Just like this line of code
was a problem that it blocked
and we fixed that by putting
on a background queue.
This one has a huge
problem which is that this
is going to set this backgroundImage
which is gonna cause this
publishing to happen up here,
which is gonna cause our
View over here to redraw
which means UI is going to be happening
on a background thread.
And that is never allowed, that is,
and in fact when you do that,
your app is gonna start behaving funny,
might possibly even crash.
And you're gonna get little
purple warnings up here
when you're running your
app in Xcode that says,
"Ah, you drew something
outside the main queue!"
So we can never do something like this,
a line of code that would
cause drawing to happen
on non main threads.
So how do we put this
back on the main thread?
We do it the exact same
way that we put this code
on this thread originally.
But we're gonna put it on instead of
a background userInitiated
quality of service thread,
we're gonna put this DispatchQueue.main.
So it'll be the same thing.
I'm gonna asynchronously post
a little function closure
to the main queue and say go do this.
Now posting something asynchronously
basically means it gets in the queue,
that's why we call these queues, to run.
And there might be other threads
that are posting these
little function snippets
to run on the main queue.
And so this guy might have to get in line
if something else is happening.
In fact one of those might
be executing right now.
The user just touched on
something or scrolled their emojis
at the top, so the main queue is busy.
But when it's settled down, it's not busy,
it'll start attending
to its queue of requests
and eventually it will execute this.
This really is all there is
to this multithreaded programming
and it looks really simple, and it is.
But it can get you in a little trouble
as I will explain in just a minute.
But this should be enough, right.
We did what we said we were gonna do
in this fetchBackgroundImageData
is we are setting the
backgroundImage to the UIImage
from fetching that data.
So let's see it in action.
All right, here we go, pick this guy up.
And we drag him, he's
turning green, that's good,
go over here and drop!
Ah, whoa, it worked!
Now there was a slight delay.
I don't know if you noticed it.
We dropped it and it took
about a half a second
to draw this image.
And during that half second,
it was just going over
the internet to whatever
website this is on
and pulling that image over.
Let's talk a little bit though
about these asynchronous things
and why it's not always as straightforward
as you might think.
I'm gonna describe a
scenario that goes on here
and you can see why this code
is actually not quite right.
Let's say that I drag and drop an image
from a really slow server and
it's gonna take 15 seconds.
And after about three or four seconds,
as the user, I'm like,
"Ah, I'm tired of waiting
"for that image," and you go
to another one, a fast server,
and you drag a new thing in.
And of course, the fast server
gives it to your right away,
and boop, you display it.
And so now it's displaying
and maybe you go on
and you're like, "Ah, I'm
gonna add some emoji to it,"
and then the other one finally returns.
And what's it gonna do, boom,
reset your background image.
So that is really unexpected for the user.
I dragged something in.
I think it failed 'cause it took too long.
So I dragged something else in.
It was quick, it got there,
and then 10 seconds later,
boom, the old thing comes in.
So that we never would want to happen.
Now it's easily protectable against,
which is just when I go back here
to set this backgroundImage,
I'm gonna make sure
that this Data that I got
is for the background URL
that the user still wants.
We can just do it in
here and say if the URL
that I just fetched,
right, that's this URL
that I got right here.
If it equals the EmojiArt's
backgroundURL, then I'll
go ahead and load it up.
But if it's some other URL that I got
15 seconds ago, (chuckles)
then I'm just gonna do nothing.
I'm gonna ignore it.
I still fetched it, it still arrived,
but I'm not gonna waste
my time making an image
and certainly not gonna blast
it in front of the user.
So this kind of minor thing right here,
it's the kind of thing you have to be able
to protect against and be careful about
when you have this
asynchronous programming.
You can't just blindly
be posting back and forth
and not thinking about
what if things like this
take a very long time and then,
it's another one comes by.
Make sure that didn't break
anything, I'm sure it won't.
Drag our image in here.
Oop, there it is, working great.
Now that we have our image working here,
let's make it so we can pick these up
and drag them in here,
drag our emojis in here.
So that's both making it
so we can drop little texts
on our View here, but
also we got to make it
so these things are draggable
so that we're doing drag
and drop with this one.
So let's do the drop side of it first
because we already know how to drop
and it's actually really easy
to drop the emoji as well.
Over here in our View, so here's onDrop.
Right now onDrop just
lets you drop the image
for the background.
Now I'm gonna make it so that
onDrop also can drop a Text
'cause our emojis are just
little snippets of Text.
So public.text is the URI for Text.
Now in this case, I do need the location.
If you drop an emoji, I need the,
let's get rid of this
URL printing right there.
In this case, I do need the location.
So we're gonna have to do it.
Now the location that's
provided here when we drop,
I think it's actually a bug.
But it's currently in
global coordinate systems,
the coordinate system of the
entire device, basically.
Not the little coordinate
system of our little,
you know, Color here with
an Image in front of it,
which, that's bad for us.
We need to convert it to do that.
So I provided a little
extension to GeometryReader
right here, GeometryProxy,
that can convert
from some coordinate
space and we're gonna use
this little function to
convert this location
that we're given here
from global coordinates
to our View's coordinate system.
Pretty straightforward,
I'm just gonna create
a little var here location.
And I'm gonna use that GeometryProxy thing
that I just showed you
to convert that location
that we're given from the global.
So this is converting this
location from global coordinates.
Now there's another
conversion I have to do.
This location is in iOS coordinate system.
Remember the iOS coordinate system?
It's the upper left is (0, 0).
My EmojiArt, I'm gonna have its X and Y
be offset from the center.
Not just to be different, but
I actually think it's easier
to store it this way.
And so we need to convert
from iOS coordinates,
zero, zero in the upper
left, to this coordinates,
zero, zero in the middle.
Our location equals a CGPoint
and X is the location you
gave us in the iOS coordinates
but minus the GeometryReader's
proxy size.width divided by two,
and the Y is the location
you gave us in the Y
minus the geometry's
size.height divide by two.
Now here I'm using my
GeometryReader both here
to convert that and my GeometryReader here
to convert from global.
So I clearly need my GeometryReader here.
So let's put GeometryReader around this.
Then the last thing we need to do
is have this drop handler
not only take the providers
but it also needs to take the locations.
So let's enhance this
drop to take the location,
comma at location which is a CGPoint.
Now in here, right now I'm looking
for the first object to be a URL.
So if I don't find that, if not found
then I'm gonna go and see if
found equals the providers
load up objects of type String.self.
So here I was loading the
first object ofType URL,
here I'm loading all
objects ofType String.
And that has a little argument here
which is string in.
And this is gonna call
this little function
for all the strings
that are found in there.
And I'm gonna assume all
my strings are emojis.
Now this does mean I could drag
a non-emoji string (chuckles) on and that,
it's going to work, but that's okay.
So here what do I want to do?
If this happens, I'm just
gonna use my intent right here,
this document.addEmoji and
the emoji is the String
that was dropped on me and
the point is the location
that it was dropped at.
And the size is the defaultEmojiSize.
So we're gonna have
emojis that are dropped
be this defaultEmojiSize,
the same size we used
with our ScrollView at the top.
Now this is complaining
'cause let found is a let.
Let's just make it be a var
'cause now we're searching
for two things here, and
this is all we needed to do
on the drop side.
We got the location and
we're just checking for them
and adding them using this Intent, right.
Remember, everyone remember this Intent
that we added over here, AddEmoji.
The last thing we want to do is be able
to drag our emojis out.
Here are the emojis
that are in the palette.
To do this is incredibly easy.
We're just gonna say onDrag.
Now onDrag takes a function.
And this function just needs
to return the things to drag.
And these need to be NSItemProviders.
Remember NSItemProviders
are what these providers are
down here when we drop.
So there needs to be a provider.
So I need to create a
provider that essentially
provides this emoji right here.
And NSItemProvider
almost has the one I want
and something for that,
object it's called,
on NSItemProvider object
and it will take this object
and for certain known types
like Strings and Images,
it will create an ItemProvider here.
Unfortunately, this is
old Objective-C world code
imported into SwiftUI and
so we have to put this
as NSString on here.
This is because
ItemProviders will only take
these old NS things.
You see it starts with
NS, this starts with NS.
Not gonna talk about as right now.
We'll talk about it later, what it means,
but it essentially converts this emoji
which is a type String, these are Strings,
into this NS world so that
NSItemProvider can do it.
And of course we don't need
return there, actually.
So let's see if this works.
We got our drag up here,
we got our drop down here.
Let's see if we can do it.
Let's start with this background,
make sure that didn't get broken.
Oh, works fine, and let's
maybe drag earth down here.
Ooh, I see a green plus!
Oh, it didn't display.
So our drag and drop appears to be working
'cause we got the green plus.
But we don't actually draw
our emojis that are dropped
anywhere in our UI here.
We draw our palettes up here,
but we don't actually draw (chuckles)
the emojis that are dropped.
We just need to put that on top
of this white overlaid image
so I'm gonna make a ZStack,
stack these two things
on top of each other, this guy.
And this second thing that I'm
gonna put in the ZStack here
is just ForEach of all of the Emojis
in my document.
And for each one of these
things, I'm going to have
to make a View to draw it.
Now I don't currently have any var
that gives me the Emojis in the document.
And if you look over in my document,
my Model is private so I
can't look at the emojiArt
so I'm gonna need another
var here which is emojis
and it's gonna be of type
Array of EmojiArt.Emoji.
And this thing is just going
to return my emojiArt.emojis
since this is a get only computed var.
This is a read-only version
of this emojiArts, okay.
That's kind of exactly what
my ViewModel here wants to do
is provide a read-only access to the Model
since it provides immutable
access via its Intent functions.
So inside here, these
emojis are Identifiable.
That's great, we made emoji Identifiable.
And to display them, it's
just Text of the emoji.
That's all we need to do.
The only thing about that
is we want to set the font
to be the size and we want to
set the position of this thing
to be wherever the
position is in the Model.
So we're gonna have to
do both of those things.
So I'm gonna create little
functions to do that.
So let's have the font return
self.font for this Emoji
and then we'll have the
position return to self.position
for this emoji.
And for that, because of
the coordinate system space
between (0, 0) in the
middle or upper left,
I'm gonna have to pass this
geometry.size in there.
So let's make these two little functions
and then I think we'll be
done here, font and position,
private func font
for emoji, EmojiArt.Emoji.
These are gonna return a Font.
And this one's pretty simple to do.
We're just going to do Font.system size.
And we need to get the size.
Now this size is actually
in the Emoji as size.
But this is an Int, right.
Size is an Int in our Model over here.
And I don't really want my
View to ever have to deal
with Ints.
So I'm gonna put something in my ViewModel
just like I did all these things,
doing a little interpretation
here into floats and points.
I'm gonna do the same thing over here
for the font size and
for the location as well.
But I'm gonna do it in an unusual way.
I'm gonna create an
extension to EmojiArt.Emoji
and I'm gonna add the var
fontSize which is a CGFloat
and just takes a CGFloat-ized version
of self.size.
Now this might feel like
we're violating MVVM here.
I just added a CGFloat var to my Model.
But this is not violating MVVM
because this code is in
my ViewModel right here.
It's not in the Model,
I'm adding it to something
that's in my Model, but this code,
this line of code right here
is here in my ViewModel.
And that makes it perfectly legal.
ViewModel is allowed to
do CGFloat, no problem.
I can do the same thing here
with location which is CGPoint.
And I could make that a CGPoint
where the X is CGFloat sub X
and the Y is CGFloat sub Y.
So now I've made it so
that we don't have to deal
with Ints ever in our View.
And our ViewModel is just
being a good ViewModel,
okay by interpreting the Model for us.
So over here then I can
just say that this size
equals this Emoji's fontSize.
And this will be a CGFloat.
And for the position, similarly
for private func position
for emoji, EmojiArt.Emoji in size, CGSize.
That's going to give the CGPoint
which is where that thing goes.
That's just gonna make a
CGPoint where we convert again
to that (0, 0) in the middle
instead of (0, 0) in the upper left.
So that's the X being Emoji's location.x
plus, plus size.width divided by two
and the Y is the Emoji's location.y.
Again, this emoji.location,
those are CGPoints
coming from our ViewModel there.
Plus size.height divided by two.
Now you might have some more
conversion going on later
when you start allowing these things
to be positioned, moved around.
And what do we got here, oh yes of course,
it's not just emoji, it's emoji's text.
So let's take a look!
Hopefully that just ForEach'd
all of us text in there.
Again, let's make a nice background here.
Let's pick this up, put it
in here, whoo, we got it!
A little baseball, yay!
Apple on top of the house, nice!
Now your homework assignment
next week is going to be,
it'll make it so you can
click on these to select them
and then drag them around, okay?
Or even pinch, which you
can do on your simulator
by holding down the option key
and pinch to zoom in and out on them.
So to get you started on
that and understanding
how to do that, in the next lecture
we're gonna make it so
that we can drag around
and pinch the whole image.
So I'm gonna let you drag around
You're gonna make it
so you can drag around
and pinch the little emoji there.
So that's it for this lecture,
and then we'll start off the next lecture
with a little bit of slides about how
to do these gestures, pinches,
and drags and all that stuff
and then we'll dive
right back into this demo
and make some more progress.
- [Presenter] For more, please
visit us at stanford.edu.