本字幕由志愿者义务贡献，采用许可协议
知识共享 署名—非商业性使用—相同方式共享 3.0 美国
>> [旁白] 斯坦福大学
好耶，第五节
斯坦福大学 2020 年春季学期 CS193p
Today we are going to start
off with a little demo
of access control in Memorize.
Access control is something
you've all already read about
in your reading assignments
and we actually used access
control a little tiny bit
in Memorize, but now it's
time to apply access control
to all of Memorize and
to use it going forward
and you should be using it
in all your SwiftUI programming
forever going forward.
After the demo, we're gonna come back
and talk a little bit about ViewBuilder.
Very important, pretty
simple little concept
and I have mentioned it a
few times in past lecture,
but now we just wanna clearly clarify
what ViewBuilder is all about.
Then we're gonna go to
the main topic of the day,
which is Shapes.
What if I want to draw my View
instead of making my
View out of other Views?
How do I do that?
And we will do a demo in
Memorize where we add a Shape,
that little pie that's behind the emoji
that you saw in lecture one,
and then we're gonna move
on to the topic of animation
and we're gonna realize that
animation is super important
in a mobile app and also
that it's super easy in Swift
almost just for free in some ways,
but when we start talking about animation
we're gonna rapidly get to this point
where we need to talk
about this other concept
called ViewModifiers.
ViewModifiers are fundamental
to how we're building these Views
and you've been using
ViewModifiers all over the place
and probably just not even
realizing you're doing it
and we're gonna dive into
exactly what's going on
in all that SwiftUI code
that you're writing.
By the way, following along
is not required this week
by the homework.
In fact, your homework this week
is not even going to be Memorize.
It's time for you to
write your own application
from scratch.
But this access control stuff
that I'm going to do right now
is something that you're
gonna have to apply
to all your code.
So following along with Memorize
might be a good learning experience.
And later in the quarter it's
quite possible we'll come back
to Memorize as a homework thing,
you're not done with Memorize yet.
And in that case I will
do my best to make it
so that the code that I'm
gonna show you this week
does not have to be included
in future homework submissions
of Memorize.
I can't a hundred percent promise that,
but I'm hoping to make that be the case.
Having said that, a lot of students find
that following along or
really helps them learn,
so I guess I actually
recommend that you do that.
And so let's start by diving
into this whole access
control change to Memorize.
Now, we've already used act
as control once in Memorize
only once, right here, private.
And access control is about
controlling the access
that different structs
have to each other's vars.
And by making this
Model completely private
in our ViewModel here,
we've forced the ViewModel
to make this var cards
so that the View could get the Cards,
and of course we want to have this Intent
so that if someone wants
to change the Model,
they have to express their
intent, how they want to do it
and that was good, that made this private.
However we could have taken
this one step further.
In our Model, the Cards themselves
probably want to be private.
Why is that?
Well we don't want anyone going in here
and mucking with these Cards.
Setting them isMatched
or even setting them face up or face down.
Whether a Card is matched
is purely in the purview
of this MemoryGame Model.
Only it knows whether
Cards should be matched
and all that logic is
in here in choose card.
So we really would want
to make this private.
But making this private is
actually gonna be a problem.
If we go back here and
look at this line of code
and compile it now with
that private in there,
you can see we get an error.
It says cards is inaccessible
due to private protection level.
And indeed the Cards are now private
and so the ViewModel is no longer allowed
to access this var.
But the ViewModel does need to access
at least to read the Cards.
How else are we gonna
show the Cards in our UI?
So we can't really have this be private,
but we can use a different
access control level
which is set.
Private set means setting this is private,
but reading it is not.
And that's exactly what
we want in this case.
We want people to able
to look at our Cards
so they can put them in
the UI, display them.
However, when it comes
to changing the Cards,
we definitely want that
reserved for ourself.
So private set, a real common
access control to want to set.
Now access control is not just
something we set on our vars.
This is something we can
also set on our functions
and our own internal computer vars.
For example,
indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
here in our Model, that's
purely a private thing.
That's private logic how
we figure out how to do
our matching game.
This definitely wants to be private.
We certainly wouldn't
want anyone setting this,
that could totally mess us up
and we really don't even
want someone looking at it
because if they started looking at it
they might depend on it
and then now I have to always
use this particular strategy
to do my logic I might not want,
so that's what we have
to keep this private.
Of course choose can't be private.
It is the way that people play our game
and our init doesn't wanna be private.
You are allowed to have private inits.
It'd be a rare circumstance,
but you could have init's only
used inside of your struct
to create maybe private instances
that this is going to use.
Now struct Card is kind
of interesting here.
You probably are thinking,
oh, private set, private set,
private set, private set.
We don't want anybody to be setting these.
However, the only way you can get a Card
outside of our Model
is through this Array.
And this Array is already private set.
This is a value type.
The actual Cards are in this Array.
When someone calls this var to get this,
they're getting a copy
and that copy is read only
because of private set.
So since there's no way for
anyone to get a writeable Card,
it's perfectly fine for us
to leave these vars this way.
Okay, what about back in
our ViewModel over here?
Clearly access to the Model.
This doesn't have to be private.
It's read only anyway
'cause it's a read only var.
Definitely Intents have be non-private.
How else will people express their intent?
But this createMemoryGame,
this static func
that probably wants to be private.
We likely do not want other people,
especially our View, to
be creating a MemoryGame.
Creating a MemoryGame, creating our Model,
that's something we do.
In your homework you have
to have a new game function.
You might well be creating
a new MemoryGame here,
but that's gonna have to
happen in your ViewModel
because there's no way
that Views, for example,
could take responsibility
for creating a Model.
So the ViewModel really wants
this to be private function.
What about in our View?
So here's our View over here.
Now let's look at CardView.
It's kind of an interesting one.
It's got these drawing
constants down here.
Those definitely can be private.
There's really no reason
that anyone would be, they're
lets anyway, but there's no reason someone
will want to be accessing
these things down here,
so this can definitely be private.
This var body has to be non-private
'cause the system is going to call that.
That's, how it gets the body for our View
and it's gonna be calling
in any time it needs to
to find out how to draw this CardView.
But this little helper function
that we call from inside
our GeometryReader,
there's no reason for
that to be public, okay?
Only we call that from our own code
inside of CardView here.
What about this var?
Can this be private?
No, because when we create a CardView,
we are required to give
this thing an initial value,
so we have to be able to access it here.
If we made this private,
then we wouldn't be able to
set it when we created it
and this will be uninitialized
and that was not allowed in Swift.
What about up here?
Well, again, var body has to be public
and also the ViewModel here
is going to have to be public
because for example, when
we create our previewer,
we're specifying the ViewModel,
and over here in our little SceneDelegate,
when we're creating the main
View of our window of our app,
we're expressing it here.
So again, this has to be public for that.
What about down here in Grid?
So in Grid, it's an
interesting case in Grid.
Do these vars have to be public?
Well, not really because we
have this public initializer
that sets these vars.
So we could make these fully private
and that would be perfectly fine.
These vars only needed to be public
if you're gonna ask people
to initialize them directly.
But since we have an
initializer to initialize them,
they don't need to be public.
Probably would want these to be private.
Var body has to be public, of course.
But again, these little
body helper functions,
they don't need to be public.
How about here in GridLayout?
So we've got GridLayout.
Of course we need the constructor
or the initializer to be public
and we need the itemSize
and location to be public,
otherwise, how are people gonna use it?
But these vars, very important
to make these private set.
Why is it so important to make
these three vars private set?
These three vars are calculated
from the initializer,
the values that come through
in the initializer are here.
And if we didn't make these private set,
someone might think that
they can reset this size var
and that these would automatically reset.
But that's not true.
Once you initialize the
GridLayout, it's fixed forever.
So we want people to know that
they can only read these
values out of here.
You can't set this and
expect these to change
or something as such.
So that's a case where access control
actually helps people understand
how to use this thing.
Okay, obviously our firstIndex,
we want that public.
We're adding that to all Arrays.
Same thing with our var only.
We're doing that public.
So that's it.
That's how we got our access
control set up in Memorize.
Every time we add new functions,
and when you do this in your homework,
you should definitely be putting privates
wherever things should be private.
Now many of you are already
working on your homework.
You haven't done this yet,
I encourage you to go do it.
We're not gonna hold
you accountable for it
in assignment number two,
but we definitely will in
assignment number three.
Let's run our app
and make sure that putting
all this private worked
and it did.
Sometimes you'll run your
app and you'll realize,
oh, I made that private but
this thing actually needs it.
And then you have to decide,
does it really want us to access that?
And if so, should it be
private set or just private?
So that's it for our little
access control foray.
Let's get back to our slides
and talk more about ViewBuilder.
So ViewBuilder is based
on a general technology
that was added to Swift recently
to support list-oriented syntax.
There's a lot of things that
are expressed as a list,
like HTML for example, it's just a list.
A paragraph and then an embedded thing
and then another paragraph,
header or whatever,
they're just listed on the page.
And so it'd be nice in Swift
to be able to represent these
somewhat native list-oriented syntaxes.
And once you have this mechanism
then you rapidly realize,
oh, there's a lot of places
where we just want a list of View,
like the front of our Cards.
We just wanna list the
two RoundedRectangles
and the emoji.
So ViewBuilder lets developers do this
and @ViewBuilder is the key word.
It's again, not part of the language.
@ViewBuilder is like @Published
or @ObservedObject,
it's the thing that's based
on these other technologies.
But @ViewBuilder, this
keyword can be tagged
onto any function that returns some View.
So as long as a function
returns some View,
you can tag that function
with @ViewBuilder
and now the compiler will interpret
what's in the curly
braces of that function
to be a list of Views, instead
of just arbitrary code,
a list of Views.
That's how ViewBuilder works.
Now that function that you're tagging
with @ViewBuilder,
it returns some View
which is a single View.
So ViewBuilder, that's why
it's called ViewBuilder,
it builds that list of
Views into a single View.
That one View that it combines it to
many times is going to be a TupleView.
So if there's two to 10
Views lifted in there,
it's gonna be a TupleView.
TupleView has up to 10 don't cares,
which are the 10 Views in there.
And notice it is limited to 10.
So if you started having
more than 11 Views,
you're gonna have to
break it up into groups,
TupleViews of TupleViews to
get that many Views in there.
It's pretty rare to imagine
having more than 10 Views
just listed straight in a row.
You're almost certainly
going to be breaking that up
with some kind of
sub-Views like CardViews,
the sub-View of our
EmojiGameView, et cetera.
So it's not really much of a
limitation but it is there.
The other kind of View could be maybe
as a ConditionalContent View,
under-bar ConditionalContent View,
and that's what the View creates
when there's an if-else in there.
Remember that the if-elses
inside of ViewBuilder
are just to choose which Views
get included in the list,
like whether it's the
front of the CardViews
or the back of the CardView.
And so that's going to create
this ConditionalContent View
which just has the predicate
to test against isFaceUp
and then it has the two Views,
might be a TupleView or some other View
that it's going to choose from.
Could even be an EmptyView
that's allowed as well.
I don't know why you would
want that necessarily,
but you could have it.
But the most important
thing to remember is that
it can be any combination of these things.
So you could have a TupleView
or one of the things in the
TupleView is a conditional View
and inside that conditional View
there's another TupleView, et cetera.
And that lets you build these
kind of arbitrarily complex
conditional lists of Views
and that's really what
this thing is all about.
Now note that some of this ViewBuilder API
is not fully public.
Like see that under-bar
ConditionalContent,
Obviously something with an
under-bar in the front of it
is not ready for prime
time, it's not fully public.
I'll bet if you look that
up in the documentation
you won't even find anything there,
but that's okay, because
we actually don't care
what kind of Views these are.
TupleViews, ConditionalContent, whatever,
all that we care is that
it's some View, right?
We can only tag a function
that returns some View
with this thing.
That's all we care about.
All of these things are some View
and so that's good enough for us.
Again, any function, also
read-only computed vars
can also be tagged with this ViewBuilder
and tagging it on there just
makes it so that function
is interpreted as a ViewBuilder.
Here's a sample from our Memorize.
Let's say that I wanted to
factor out the front of the Card,
those two RoundedRectangles
and the Text that you see here
into its own little function.
Well I could have func, front of card,
it returns some View
and in here I would normally
have to put it in a Group
or something like that,
but instead I can just
mark it @ViewBuilder
and now the curly braces within there
is going to be interpreted
as a list of Views.
And I could have if-thens
and stuff in here,
if I wanted to do the whole
Card inside here I could
and have the if isFaceUp,
all that stuff perfectly allowed.
This is just a list of
Views with those if-thens
allowed in there.
This particular green code
would return a TupleView
where it's three don't cares
are RoundedRectangle,
RoundedRectangle, Text.
Of course there are two
TupleViews with eight don't cares
and nine or this will
be the one with three.
And again we don't care that
it's doing a TupleView there.
Absolutely don't care.
All we care is this some View.
Now you could also use this @ViewBuilder
to mark parameters to functions
that are themselves functions
that return some View.
For example, our viewForItem
argument to Grid, right?
That was a function that took an Item
and returned a View, and
that would be eligible
to be marked with @ViewBuilder.
Now we didn't do that in Grid
and I'll talk about that
in a second, why we didn't,
but someone who does do
that is GeometryReader
and HStack and VStack and
ForEach they all do this,
but let's look at what the declaration
of GeometryReader's initializer
probably looks like.
You've got GeometryReader, right?
It's got this don't care Content,
which is constrained to be a View.
So the initializer for GeometryReader
we know takes content,
this curly brace thing,
that gives you the GeometryProxy,
the thing that we get the size out of,
and it returns Content that's some View.
So since this content argument
is a function that returns some View,
it can be marked @ViewBuilder
which GeometryReader does.
It marks it @ViewBuilder.
That means that what's
inside your GeometryReader's,
little curly braces, is a list of Views,
is going to be interpreted
as a list of Views.
It's as simple as that.
And it's usually up to
things like GeometryReader,
Hstack, VStack,
to decide whether the argument
that you're passing them
makes sense to be a list of Views.
And for those guys that's
what they determine.
Now, you might ask, why
didn't we do this in Grid?
Grid is asking you to provide
a View for a certain item
and we pass a function.
Why didn't we say @ViewBuilder
for our View for item argument in Grid?
Well the answer had its part
to do with this thing where
ViewBuilder's still kind of private.
It's implementation for example,
has no way to extract the Views
from a TupleView, ConditionalContent,
it's just you can't get them out of there.
So there's no way Grid could
know what they all are.
That's not public in the
current @ViewBuilder.
I'm sure this will be made public
and eventually you could do it
and then maybe it might make
sense to have Grid's argument,
but even then Grid is a
two-dimensional Array.
That's usually gonna be
a fair number of Views.
It's unlikely you're
gonna be listing them,
especially if you're gonna
have 10 or less of them,
possible, but unlikely.
So the fact that Grid
gets in bed with ForEach
and represents it the
same way ForEach does
is probably just fine.
Just before we leave ViewBuilder,
I'd just like to reiterate this.
This slide is nothing new.
Things that are marked ViewBuilder
are just a list of Views.
Yes, there's conditional in there
to see whether you include
a View in the list,
but there's just a list of Views.
So no vars can be declared in there,
you can't have arbitrary code.
Anytime you have something
that's a ViewBuilder,
it's just this list of Views
with the if-thens in there
to pick which Views.
Main topic of the day, Shape.
Shape is a protocol.
It inherits from View,
so all Shapes are Views.
So you can always put a
Shape in a ZStack or whatever
as we saw,
RoundedRectangle, we threw
it in there, no problem.
There are of course built in common Shapes
like RoundedRectangle, there's Circle,
there's Capsule which is a
kind-of oval sort of thing
and other ones in there.
Now Shapes draw themselves by default
by filling themselves with
the current foreground color.
We saw this with the backs of our Cards.
They take a RoundedRectangle,
it just by default fills.
But we also learned that
we can call stroke or fill
with arguments to change
the way the Shape looks.
Now I wanna talk about fill and stroke
and the arguments that
can be passed to it.
It might have looked like,
when we did our Memorize code,
that the argument that's passed
to fill is actually a Color
because you'll remember that
the second RoundedRectangle
from the back, actually no,
the rectangle all the way
in the back, is white.
And then we put the
stroked one on top of it.
So that white one we
said fill Color.white.
So it seemed like, oh, fill takes a Color.
But in fact fills argument is not a Color
and I'm gonna take this
opportunity with fill and stroke
to talk about another feature in Swift
called generic functions.
You already know about generic types
like Array and like our MemoryGame,
it has CardContent as a don't care.
Well, functions can have
don't cares as well.
They can be generic as well.
And they do this similar kind of syntax.
You can see that fill
has this don't care S,
what to fill with type S,
see that's a type of S,
and it's constraining it
so that it's not a full don't care
it's kind of like a care a little bit
where that S has to implement
the ShapeStyle protocol.
So this ShapeStyle protocol,
we're not gonna talk about it,
but if you implement
this ShapeStyle protocol,
then you can be used to
fill or stroke a Shape.
What kinds of things implement ShapeStyle?
Well Color, obviously we know
'cause we've called fill with Color,
but also ImagePaint,
which takes JPEG image
and tiles it in there to paint with
as if it were a paintbrush of
that image just painting it.
Also there are Gradients,
angular and linear Gradients
that show a band of colors or whatever.
So these things are all quite different,
Color, Gradient, ImagePainting,
very different things,
and really fill doesn't
care what they are.
That's why S is a don't care.
But it does care 'cause they
all implement this ShapeStyle
'cause if they don't
implement the ShapeStyle
then a Shape doesn't
really know how to use them
to do the fill and stroke.
Again, I'm mostly showing you this,
yes, so that you can know
that you can fill with Images
or Gradients or Colors,
but also so you should realize
that there are these generic functions,
functions that have don't cares
as the types of some of their arguments.
What if you wanna create your own Shape?
You don't wanna use
RoundedRectangle, Circle,
whatever, you want your own Shape.
Well, the Shape protocol uses an extension
to implement View's
body var for you, right?
'Cause Shape inherits from
View, so Shape is a View.
So it would have to
implement the body var.
All Views have to implement that body var.
But Shape implements that for you.
The protocol and
extension of that protocol
implements it for you.
However, Shape introduces a new func
that you are required to implement.
It's called path in rect.
So this function path in
rect is going to just return
something called a Path.
Now a Path has a whole
bunch of functions on it,
like line to and arc and Bezier curve.
All these things that
let you essentially draw
like you're drawing with a pen.
And so you're going to build some Path
by drawing with this
pen and return it here.
Now, once you return it, now
Shape has all it needs to know
to do what it does,
which is provide a Shape that
can be stroked and filled.
Now this is best shown, how
this works, with a demo.
So we're gonna go back to Memorize
and implement that little pie.
If you remember from our first lecture
there was that little pie and it animated
and it kind of ran the clock down
so that if you match the card fast enough,
you got extra points.
So we're gonna draw that
pie in our memory game.
We're not gonna animate it yet.
Animation is our next topic.
We will get back to that.
So today we're just learning
how to create our own Shape
by building that pie.
I've taken a screenshot of
that video of the game in play
so that we can see what
it is we're shooting for.
We're trying to build this
little pie chart thing
that maybe looks like
a Pac-Man or something
behind our ghost.
And there's no such Shape
built in to SwiftUI,
this kind of Pac-Man Shape,
so we're gonna have to
build this ourselves.
But before we start
building this custom Shape,
let's just try and get a circle
behind this ghost right here.
'Cause we know there is
this built-in Circle,
just like there's a big built
in RoundedRectangle here.
So to do that, pretty straightforward.
Here's our View, here's our CardView.
Right here and here is
yep, here's the background.
Here's where our emoji is
and this Circle kind of just wants to live
right in between here,
right between the
background and the emojis.
So let's see.
This just works.
Maybe this is all we need to get started.
All right, let's click.
Oh that's actually getting there.
Take a look.
Oh, that's pretty close.
Now it's not quite right.
It's a little too close
to the edges there,
there's supposed to be a little gap,
and this color is a little
too bright of orange,
but it's in the ballpark.
Now we could go back
here and try and fix this
and then run again and then fix some more
and then run again and tweak it some more.
But that's a little tedious
and of course we have a
much better tool for that,
which is our canvas over here
and we can just resume and
see what our thing looks like
and it looks like...
Oh no, all the cards are face down.
Which kind of makes sense
because that's how game starts,
but it's kind of useless to me
to have all these cards face down.
I really want at least one
of these cards to be face up
so I can be working on this.
How do we do that?
Turns out that this
code down at the bottom
that I pushed out of the way,
it's not as scary as
maybe I made it out to be
by pushing it out of the way.
This is really just a static
var that is of type, some View
that is returning this
whole View to preview our
EmojiMemoryGameView.
And right now we're creating one
an EmojiMemoryGameView.
and we're giving it this ViewModel
that we just created on the fly.
But there's no reason
that we couldn't just
take this out of here,
put it in a variable, I'll call it game,
ask that game to choose one of the Cards,
how about choose the
first card in the game,
something like that,
and then use that game here
as the thing that we're going to preview.
Of course we have to return
since we don't have a one line function,
and voila, right away we're
seeing the face-up Card
and I could maybe have
it choose the third Card
and now it's showing me the third Card.
So I could have it pick a couple of Cards.
Of course, if I pick three Cards,
then it's going play the game and match.
But this is perfect for our needs.
We can go back up here and
start working on this Circle
and try to make it look more
like we're intending over here.
Let's start by trying to
get it in from the edge
a little bit so it doesn't
smash into the edge.
We know how to do that.
Just put some padding around this Circle.
Well, now, that's not quite
what we're looking for.
A little too much padding.
How about if we just, I don't know,
put less padding around there?
Yeah, I'm pretty happy with that.
Although my ghost there is a little big,
I don't think I wanna smash
in right up at the edge there.
So maybe I'll go down to my
control panel of constants here
and change this to like 0.7 yeah,
maybe 0.65 no, 70% that looks good.
I don't want this to be too small.
This is the purpose of that
card is really to show this.
So I don't wanna go too small there.
What about this really
kind of vivid orange?
Well, it turns out we can make an orange
that's kinda light or kinda
see through right here
by making it semi-transparent.
And View has an awesome
modifier for that, opacity,
it's called, takes a double between zero,
which means completely transparent
to one, completely opaque.
Now we can go in the
middle, maybe like 70%,
maybe 10% oh it's too light.
30%, 40%, I kinda like 40%.
I think that's what I
ended up with over here.
It's close, something like that.
You can see we've got this
really looking the way we want
except that this is a
Circle instead of our pie.
To do our Pac-Man pie thing,
we just need to replace Circle right here
with our own custom Shape.
So let's do that, let's create that.
I'm gonna go File, New
because we're creating a new thing here.
It is gonna be a SwiftUI View
because Shapes are Views,
but if we pick this template,
we're gonna get that var body
and the Shape protocol
provides that for us.
So we're just gonna pick
Swift file right here,
make sure we put it in the right place.
I'm gonna call it Pie, is
the name of my custom Shape.
Let's create that.
Here we go.
Now of course Shapes are
very much a UI thing,
so we're gonna import
SwiftUI, not Foundation there.
And creating a Shape, so easy, struct Pie.
It conforms to the Shape protocol
just constrains and gains with that,
and it's gonna gain the
fact that it's a View
and it can be filled and
stroked, all kinds of gains,
and the only real constraint
here is this func,
that's called path in rect,
and it returns a Path
that we have to create,
and this Path is just
going to be the edges
of what we're drawing.
So for us it's gonna start
here in the middle and go up,
around here, back to the middle.
That is the Path that we're gonna build.
And we're gonna build that
with functions in Path
like draw a line to here
and draw an arc over here.
We're just gonna combine all those
to make this nice path.
And once we do, Shape we'll
take care of all the rest.
Being able to fill it and all that
is gonna all be taken care of for us.
How do we return this path thing?
I'm just gonna create an empty
one, I'll call it p Path.
That's an empty Path,
and I'm gonna return it.
And in between here I just
have to call functions in Path
that move around, draw the
lines that I wanna draw.
Now what is this rect that's passed to us?
That is the rect in which we're
supposed to fit our Shape.
Now almost all, if not all Shapes
usually use all the space in
the rect that's given to them
and yes, you guessed it,
because Shape is a View,
the rect it's gonna give you here
is the space that was offered to it.
Space offered to it.
We've got this Path, got this rect,
how are we gonna do this?
Let's start by gonna the
center of the rectangle.
So we're gonna be given
this rectangle to draw in.
Let's go right to its
center and start there,
right here, and then we're gonna move up.
So let's start in the middle.
So getting the middle is pretty easy.
I'm just gonna go to the
middle by saying p Path,
that's this Path, dot move to the center.
And center is gonna be a var.
Let center equal.
To get the center I'm just
gonna create a CGPoint.
Now notice that all of
these drawing things,
not just CGFloat, but
CGRect, CGPoint, CGSize
that we saw with GeometryReader,
they all start with CG.
This CG stands for Core Graphics.
That's the underlying graphics system
that all this is built on.
So finding the center of
this rect is really easy.
The X position is just the rect midX
and the Y is the rectangles midY.
So that's it.
We got the center, we're
started already here,
but we haven't drawn anything.
We haven't actually drawn
any lines or anything.
So the next thing we're gonna do
is draw a line from the center up to here.
Now I'm gonna make it so that my Pie,
this starting angle and this ending angle,
can be anything you want.
So you can make your Pie a
small little piece of pie
or big pie pointing in any direction.
So I'm gonna need a couple of vars
One is gonna be my starting angle
and one is my ending angle.
So let's put those vars in our Shape.
This is just a struct.
So he can have vars startAngle,
but what type would the angle be?
Well, you could make it a
CGFloat or something like that,
but there's a really nice
thing in Swift called Angle
and I'll show you that in a second.
So we're gonna make these start
and end angles, the Angles.
What is an Angle?
Let's go ahead and take a look
at it in the documentation.
Here it is, struct
Angle, it's just a struct
It lets you create an Angle
using degrees or using radians.
Hopefully everyone remembers
from trigonometry class
what radians are, right?
Degrees zero to 360
around the circle,
radians it's zero to 2π.
2πr that's the circumference of a circle.
So radians is zero to
2π around the circle.
And notice this Angle's animatable.
That's gonna be nice for us later.
Also it can be hashed,
that means a can be put in
a dictionary or hash table.
We don't need to do that,
but this Angle, very nice
little type for us.
I need to somehow
calculate a start position
up at the top up here,
this little position here,
so that I can draw a
line from here to here.
So I'm gonna draw that line by saying
addLine to the start at the top there.
So I need start.
How about start equals a
point also, so CGPoint.
Let's go ahead and put
this on multiple lines
and have the X on one line
and the Y on another line.
So the X position, horizontal position,
is the center's X plus
the radius of our circle,
which we're gonna have to figure out,
times, and again, I'm
hoping you're remembering
your trigonometry from
eighth grade or ninth grade
or whenever trigonometry
is taught these days,
and I wanna do the cosine
of that start angle,
and I have to do it in radians
because this cosine function
in Swift does radians,
and also I wanna do this
all in CGFloat world,
not in Double's.
And similarly the Y is
just the center dot Y
plus the radius times
the sine of the CGFloat
startAngle dot radians.
And so I need the radius.
What's gonna be the
radius of my circle here?
Well, I could make it the width
or I could make it the height.
I really want it to be
the smaller of the two.
So in this case I definitely
don't wanna have my radius
be half the height of this space
because then it's gonna be way too big.
So I'm gonna pick the smaller
of the width or height
and divide it by two so that it's radius
instead of diameter.
So let's do that and let
our radius equal the minimum
of the rect's width and
the rect's height and
we divide by two.
So I think that's all we need to do
to get up to that point
up at the top over here.
Now we need to go in this big arc.
Okay, turn this arc.
Luckily Path has a function
for arcing as well.
It's called addArc and you
can do it different ways.
I'm gonna choose the simplest one here,
which lets you create an arc
by specifying the center of
the arc, the radius of the arc,
the start angle, and the end angle,
and whether you're going
clockwise around the arc,
or counter-clockwise, right?
So whether we're gonna go
counterclockwise like this
or whether we're gonna
go clockwise like this.
So let's give this center.
We know the center it's
that center radius.
Yep, we know that too.
Start angle?
Yeah, we know the start angle.
End angle?
Yeah, that's this var up here.
This is really easy.
And how about clockwise?
This is a boolean, whether
we're going clockwise,
let's allow people using
us to tell us that too.
So we'll say clockwise is a Bool,
put clockwise down here.
And let's not make them say it though.
We'll have a default, we'll
have a clockwise false.
That happens to be the
way we wanna go, right?
Counter clockwise, so
we'll do clockwise false
work for our Pie.
But this is just a default,
we had to pick one of them,
we might as well pick this one.
That's the arc.
We're almost done with
our little Path here.
It goes around, now it needs
to come back to the middle.
So we need a line back
to the center there.
So that's p dot addLine to the center.
And that is it.
We have done a custom Shape here.
All we had to do was define
this Path and return it,
and we have a custom Shape.
Shape is gonna take
care of everything else,
filling it, stroking it, all that stuff
it knows how to do that.
So let's go back to our View
and where we used Circle right here,
we're gonna use our Pie instead.
So let's do Pie.
Oops, sorry, quit Xcode there.
Let's get our thing back here.
Sorry about that.
We know that Pie has some vars.
I'm gonna initialize the
starting angle and the end angle.
Notice that the clockwise
is an optional one.
We don't have to specify that.
So let's choose to do the
start and end angles here.
Now what angles are we
looking to start at here?
Well, we want to start straight up here
and go counterclockwise over to here.
So the straight up that's
probably Angle dot degrees zero,
and then the end angle,
where are we ending?
We are ending over here.
Well if this is zero and this would be 90
so this would be like what, 110 degrees,
something like that.
Let's try that Angle dot degrees 110.
Oh, that didn't quite work.
What is going on here?
This does not look anything like this.
So why is this a problem?
Well, the first thing to understand in iOS
is that Angle zero,
zero degrees is not up,
it's out to the right.
Angle zero's out to the right.
So if we wanted this to
be in the kind of degrees
where zero is straight up,
we're gonna have to subtract 90 degrees
from all these angles.
So 90 degrees off of that one
and 90 degrees off of that one.
But that didn't really work either.
That's still not what we're
looking for over here.
It looks like it started up here at zero,
but it went clockwise
instead of counterclockwise.
I'm certain over here that
I said clockwise false.
Yeah, counter-clockwise.
What's going on?
That's impossible, that
couldn't possibly be happening.
Well, this is happening because in iOS,
the drawing coordinate
system that you're drawing in
right here,
has (0, 0) in the upper
left and is upside down.
So this is increasing Y.
Starting up here at (0, 0)
Y is getting bigger as we get down here.
It's not Cartesian coordinates
that you're used to
from your trigonometry class.
This is not (0, 0),
this is (0, 0) up here.
So since this whole thing is upside down,
clockwise and counterclockwise
are going the other way as well.
So we actually need this
start angle, end angle,
and we also want clockwise true.
So even though we're really
going the opposite direction,
we're having to say clockwise true.
And sure enough, that has
given us exactly what we want.
Now in the next lecture, we
will start animating this.
For example, we'll have
it still start at zero,
but as the time ticks down,
it'll go from 110, 150,
200,
300,
it's ticking down 350,
times almost up 360 times up.
So we're going to just animate this Angle
going down to zero.
That's all gonna be in the next lecture
when we talk about animation.
The first thing we're gonna
talk about in animation though
is animating Views.
Views are coming and going,
they're getting larger and smaller.
Sometimes they're doing special thing
like a CardView might flip over.
Okay, kind of do a 3D
rotation to flip over.
Now View animation is
not done in the same way.
Shapes are animated, they
animate themselves directly.
Views are animated
through their modifiers.
And so to understand how to animate Views,
we're gonna have to take
a time out from animation
and talk about what is a ViewModifier.
Now you've been using ViewModifiers
all over the place so far in Memorize,
aspectRatio, padding,
font, foregroundColor.
All of these things are ViewModifiers.
They modify a View and return a new View
that is a modified version
of View you called them on.
That's what ViewModifiers do.
Now most of these modifiers,
not all, but most of them,
are probably implemented by
just turning right around
and calling a very important
function in View protocol,
added to the View protocol via extension
called modifier.
This function modifier in View,
it takes one argument,
which is essentially
something that implements
the ViewModifier protocol.
So here aspectRatio 2/3
and I've left off the fit
and fill for space reasons,
but aspectRatio 2/3
is likely doing something
like calling on the View,
on the same View that you're
sending your aspectRatio to,
it's saying dot modifier,
AspectModifier, which
is some struct, of 2/3.
So let's talk about what that
ViewModifier protocol is.
By its name you can probably almost guess.
It only has one function in it
and that functions only
job is to take something
and modify it to produce a View.
You could for example, adjust the space
to provide the aspectRatio 2/3,
or ViewModifier could add some
padding around the outside.
That's what the padding
ViewModifier I'm sure does.
So what does this code
look like for protocol?
So here's the protocol ViewModifier.
That first line associatedtype Content.
Again, you guys read your
reading assignment, I hope
and you understand that what
associatedtype Content is
is a don't care for protocols.
Protocols, just like functions and types
they also have don't cares,
but their syntax is
associatedtype Content,
not the angle brackets like
you would see on struct.
So the ViewModifier
protocol has a don't care
called Content.
Doesn't really care what type Content is.
All right, so now once
you understand that,
we can look at the only
function in ViewModifier,
which is body.
Body takes a Content
which is a don't care,
we don't really care what that is,
and it returns very importantly some View.
And inside that body it
just has to take the Content
that was given to it
and somehow make up a View and return it.
Now when you call dot modifier on View,
the Content that's passed
is the View you sent
dot modifier to, right?
The View you called dot modifier on,
that is the content.
That makes it so any ViewModifier
that is called with dot modifier
is going to get the View it's
called on as the Content.
That's why we say it modifies that View.
It's gonna create a new View
using that View you sent
it to as its Content.
Right, so let's see, an example of this,
to make this all more concrete.
Let's say I wanted to have a ViewModifier
that took any View like our Text ghost,
or any View an Image, anything,
and it modified it so that
it looked like a card.
Cardifies it, basically.
That's what we wanna build.
Now that sounds like that's a
pretty complicated modifier.
It's more complicated than
just putting padding around it
or something, perfectly fine though.
It's actually gonna be
quite simple modifier,
but conceptually it makes sense.
Now in our app we wouldn't
necessarily even need a modifier
like this because we only
have one kind of View
that ever gets cardified,
but you could imagine an app
where you have some cards
that have images on them, some have emoji,
some just have text or
something, other flashcards,
but they're all having the same card.
That might make sense to be
able to cardify any View.
Here's what the code would look like.
The first line there is actually
how we would call the modifier.
For example, if we wanted to cardify
our ghost text right there,
we would say dot modifier,
that very important View function
and the argument is a ViewModifier.
Now I'm gonna call my ViewModifier,
you can see struct Cardify
there in the next line.
I'm gonna call it Cardify and
it actually takes an argument.
We'll talk about that.
But eventually though, I
actually want this to say
Text goes dot Cardify,
just like I say dot
foregroundColor, dot padding,
I wanna say dot Cardify.
I don't wanna have to
say dot modifier Cardify.
So on the next slide
we're gonna show how we get
from dot modifier Cardify
to dot Cardify.
But for now, let's focus on
how we would implement
this Cardify ViewModifier
'cause this has to be something
that takes the Text ghost
and modifies it, turns it into a new View
that looks like a card.
That's what this thing's gonna do.
First thing I wanna look at
here is the Content argument
to that body function in ViewModifier.
I made it yellow here all
the places it appears,
it's the argument to body.
You can see up top the Text
ghost is what that Content is
and then also look down inside the ZStack
I'm embedding that Content, it's a View
and I'm embedding it inside my ZStack
in the same place I would've
put that back in my old code.
So now it's gonna take any
View and embed it right there
in my ZStack on the face of the card.
So do you see how this is
going to modify the View
that you send it to to look like a card.
Now, one thing to note
here that's interesting is
this ViewModifier needs some information,
needs to know whether the
card is face up or face down.
It's a struct so I just
add a var isFaceUp to it
and we know that if you have a
var and it's not initialized,
then whoever creates this struct,
which is up there in the top line,
it needs to specify the value of it.
So hopefully this is looking
from kind of familiar to you
when you do these modifiers,
obviously a lot of them take arguments
foregroundColor takes a Color
and padding can take things
like the top or bottom
and how many points to pad
and all these other arguments.
Those are just gonna be inside
the ViewModifier for padding,
for example.
So dot modifier, that
function, it returns a View,
returns something that conforms to View
that is going use this purple
contents of body right here
to draw the View.
Now modifier doesn't directly
return this purple code
returns something else that's also a View,
but that's something else
is going to use this purple
code to draw what it draws.
And simple as that.
Dot modifier is just going to
use this ViewModifier thing,
pass the View that it
is sent to to the body,
it's gonna get whatever built
into whatever's necessary
and returned as the new View to use.
And then of course since
that thing is a View,
we can send another modifier to it
and another modifier to that, et cetera
and Swift is very smart
about keeping track
when it's modifications,
modifications, modifications
so that it can do things like animation.
So how do we get from this
text dot modifier syntax
to dot Cardify,
'cause really that's
why we want dot Cardify.
Really easy, you actually
know how to do this.
I'm gonna create an extension
to the View protocol,
add the function cardify
that cardify obviously returns some View
and it's just gonna
return self dot modifier
of the Cardify.
Remember this is an extension to View,
so self is the View.
So of course I can call
dot modifier on self
and pass it the right ViewModifier,
in this case, our Cardify.
All right, so let's go implement this
in our Memorize application.
Our goal in this demo is to
make it so that any View,
including our ghost and
Pac-Man here can be cardified.
That means putting this border
around it when it's face up
or just drawing this
back when it's face down.
Let's start this demo by just imagining
what our code would look like
if we had this cardifier.
Let's make some space here so
we can see what's going on.
I'm gonna take the part
of our card right now
that's gonna get cardified,
which is just the Pie and the Text.
We're gonna separate
them out from the code
that actually is doing the cardification.
Then we're gonna take this ZStack
that has the stuff we want in it,
and I'm gonna cardify it
by saying dot cardify.
Of course the cardifier needs to know
whether this thing is face up or not.
So I'm gonna pass that is face up in there
and we're gonna see how this
is going to be specified
in a bit.
Now this code, that's the thing
that actually does the
cardification, right?
Puts the RoundedRectangles
in the back or in the front.
Just gonna cut that out of here
and I'm gonna go put that
in my Cardify ViewModifier.
Before I go over there,
I eventually do want this to say this,
but we know that really the ViewModifiers
are calling this View
function called modifier
then you just specify the
ViewModifier you want.
So the ViewModifier we're
gonna create to do this,
I'm gonna call it Cardify
and it's of course going to
have to take that face up
as an argument.
So this is what this cardifier
right here is really gonna do
and this is gonna end up being
a function we're gonna create
that it's just one line that calls this.
So we'll comment this
out and we'll put it back
once we add this one
liner that calls this.
But this is what this is going to do
and of course it says
unresolved identifier Cardify,
we have to go write the code
that does this ViewModifier.
So let's hop over and do that.
File, New File.
This is not a SwiftUI
View, it's a ViewModifier.
So we'll click this, we'll go here,
I'm gonna call this Cardify,
that's the name of my new modifier.
Notice it's not putting
it in the right place.
It's a good example of seeing that.
I don't want it in this
blue thing at the top.
I want this down here,
and this yellow folder
and I want this to be the same place
that this yellow folder is up here.
So hopefully you all are
remembering to do that
so you're not ending up with
files all over the place
they shouldn't be.
So create Cardify.
Here is Cardify.
Now of course ViewModifiers
are very much a UI thing,
so we don't say import
Foundation right there,
and creating a ViewModifier, very simple.
Struct Cardify, it's a ViewModifier
and when we do this we're
immediately gonna get an error
that says Cardify does not
conform to protocol ViewModifier.
This protocol only has one function in it,
it's called body and it takes
content as the argument.
This Content right here is
a don't care that we get
from this protocol.
So protocols can have don't cares too.
They specify them with
that associatedtype syntax
that you read about in
your reading homework
and so this can be anything.
This is a don't care.
We'll talk about what it's
gonna be in just a second.
Then of course this is a ViewModifier,
it's modifying a View and
then returning some new View
that is the modified version of this.
So this argument right here,
just to remind you from the slides
when we call back here, modifier Cardify,
the content that we're
being asked to modify
is going to be whatever
View we call modifier on.
So we're gonna be calling
modifier on the ZStack.
So inside our cardifier in this case
the content will be that ZStack.
This is always the View that
you're calling dot modifier on.
So what goes in here?
Well in here we just have
to create the modified View,
in other words, a cardified View.
So I'm just gonna paste
that thing we had before
and of course this still
has to be in a ZStack
because we still have
these RoundedRectangles
stacked on top of each other.
So let's go ahead and do that.
And we have some things undefined in here,
like cornerRadius and edgeLineWidth.
Those are over here,
that's drawing constants.
We don't need them over here anymore
since we're using
cardification to do our card.
So we'll just pop those over here.
That fixes most of our problem.
We do know that we have
to pass this is space up
as an argument here
and Cardify needs to
know whether it's face up
so it's gonna have a var
isFaceUp which is a bool
and I'm not gonna set
it equal to something
so anytime someone creates
a Cardify like here,
they have to tell me what
the value of this isFaceUp is
And then I'm gonna use
this isFaceUp inside
anytime I wanna check
and see if I'm face up.
Now what about this isMatched thing.
Well isMatched really does
not belong in Cardify.
Matching has to do with our card game.
This Cardify can Cardify any View,
not just Views in our card game.
This could put a card face
up, face down on any View.
so we wanna keep this generic.
We don't want it to be tied
to the rest of our app.
This is a nice reusable thing
we could actually use another game--
Let's say we wrote some other game
that had some Texts on
cards and Images on cards
and emoji on cards all
mixed in the same app.
Well, we can use Cardify to
Cardify any of those things.
But we couldn't really
have the matching in there
because matching is specific
to this app, Memorize.
And then the last thing we wanna do here
is obviously this Content
needs to be somewhere in here.
Well I'm gonna put it
exactly where it was before.
Just to put content.
Content is the View, the ZStack
that modifier is being sent to here.
So I'm just gonna take this,
it's going to pop right in here.
Now I've done it.
This is a ViewModifier
that takes this Content,
any View that dot modifier sent here
and it puts it in a ZStack
with the RoundedRectangles
or if it's faced up, it
does this, et cetera.
This is something that
cardifies this content.
What did, let's go back here.
Let's go ahead and run, see if this works.
It looks like the backs
of cards are working.
Let's try the front.
Ooh, this is working nicely.
Now there is one problem here
which is that if I get a match
and then I click on another
card, oh these don't go away.
That's 'cause I took that
matching stuff out of there.
So we've gotta fix that.
And the other thing we gotta fix is
we want this nicer syntax dot cardify.
So let's fix this nicer syntax first
and then we'll fix the
problem where matched cards
are are still being included here
when they should be taken away.
This function that does cardify
is just something we're gonna
add to View with an extension.
And it really makes the
most sense obviously
to put it in this file
'cause this is where the
Cardify ViewModifier is.
So this is the place we would
wanna put an extension to View
that has the func cardify.
Now cardify is also going to have to take
whether it's face up as an argument
and it's just gonna return
that cardified View,
really easy to implement.
Just gonna call self,
self is a View, we're an
extension to View here,
modifier, we're gonna give it a Cardify
with isFaceUp being this
isFaceUp that's passed to us.
And that's it.
Simple as pie.
No pun intended.
We have made cardify here
into a nice little function
that we can call on any
View just like this.
You don't need this slightly
more bulky way of doing it
and this should feel to you just like font
of some dot largeTitle,
foregroundColor Color.
What about the fact that matched
cards are not disappearing?
I'm just gonna do that by
only doing this whole card
if the card is face up or
the card is not yet matched.
The card is faced up or
I haven't matched it yet,
then boom, I'm going to
put that card up there.
Otherwise I just want blank space,
which is exactly what we had before.
Now this is giving an error here that says
function declares an opaque
return type, yep, some View,
but has no return return statements.
Oh, that's right.
There's no return statement in here.
I guess I could say
return that fixes that,
but what about in the
else case of this if.
We have this if no else,
we're not returning anything in that case.
So that's no good and I'm gonna fix this
in a kind of novel interesting way,
which is I'm just gonna make
this into a ViewBuilder.
If I turn this function
into a ViewBuilder,
then this gets now interpreted
as a list of Views.
Yes with ifs to decide whether
certain Views are in or out,
but this is a list of Views.
It's either gonna end up
being the ZStack, the View,
or it's gonna be EmptyView
if this is not true.
Look no errors, simple as that.
We've got our ViewBuilder.
Run it over here, let's try and see.
This is working.
Let's make a match and
oh, it took 'em away
'cause this if was not
true and they're gone.
Now one other thing we can do
and just make sure that our
cardify is really working,
instead of doing this ZStack,
let's try some other Views.
How about like a Circle
and let's go ahead and bring
back our canvas over here.
We can see this in action.
Yep, look at that.
It's a Circle put on a card.
We can even do Circle
with a little bit of padding on it, right?
Or maybe we'll put a Capsule in here.
That's another built in Shape Capsule.
That's what Capsule Shapes
look like if you're wondering.
We could put maybe something like Text.
Hello world, look at that, cardified that.
So cardify is a general
cardifier, ViewModifier
that we built that can modify any View.
All right, this is good
that we have done all
this ViewModifier stuff
because the next lecture we're
gonna talk about animation,
and when it comes to animating Views,
not shapes like this Pie, but
animating Views themselves,
it's all about ViewModifiers.
They were really only
animating ViewModifiers,
we don't actually
animate Views themselves.
We'll be looking into that next lecture
and seeing how we can animate this card.
Cards have a lot of
animation that they want.
They want to flip over, for example.
That's a nice animation that a card wants,
so it's really good that
we've put this cardification
to a ViewModifier so that
we can animate it next time.
That is it for today.
I will talk to you then.
>> [旁白] 请访问 stanford.edu
获取更多内容